<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jesus Nazarenus, Rex Judaeorum. Or, a tract concerning the inscription fastned by Pilates command</title>
            <author>Bourchier, John, Sir, d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73533</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3412.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124700</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898734</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898734</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152049</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73533)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152049)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2003:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jesus Nazarenus, Rex Judaeorum. Or, a tract concerning the inscription fastned by Pilates command</title>
                  <author>Bourchier, John, Sir, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>Pp. 191, [22]+   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>N. Okes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>By John Bourchier--STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1475-1640 reel 2003 misbound and has title page torn.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Christ Church, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Crucifixion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152049:1"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Pilates <hi>Jest Turned to Earnest.</hi>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>JOHN <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                     </bibl>
                     <hi>And it was</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>[IESUS OF NAZARETH KING OF THE JEWES.]</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen Satans malice had produced miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe in our firſt
<pb facs="tcp:152049:2"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152049:3"/> r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ows, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> onely in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, whom their ſoules deſired in the ſubſtance.</p>
                  <p>At length, when the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Grace was come, he that was <hi>velatus in Lege, covered in the Law,</hi> became <hi>Revelatus in Evangelio
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152049:3"/> Diſcouered in the Goſpell:</hi> For when the fulneſſe of time was come, God ſent his Son of a Woman made under the Law, that wee might receiue the Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sonnes. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4.5. The ſonne of man had ſinned againſt God, the Sonne of God ſatisfies for the ſinne of man. Let ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration produce amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But ſeeing man had ſinned for a ſeaſon, and muſt dye unto eternity, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Sonne of eternity did ſuffer for a ſeaſon: therefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> was ſlaine. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.26. but not for himſelfe: <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus eſt in mortem propter
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152049:4"/> offenſas noſtras. Rom.</hi> 4.25.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25</note> 
                     <hi>Hee was deliuered to death for our offences.</hi> Hee was delivered by his Father in mercy; by himſelfe in compaſſion; by <hi>Iudas</hi> for covetouſneſſe, and by the <hi>Iewes</hi> in malice: And all this to the end, that God might effect, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the <hi>Iews</hi> could not conjecture, the Redemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> of his people <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the precedent Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you have Chriſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, in this Crucified. Hee that was typified by the <hi>Brazen Serpent,</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted on the Croſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two Theeves, with this Title ſuperſcribed, <hi>[Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152049:4"/> of Nazareth, King of the Iewes.]</hi> As the manner of Chriſts Death, ſo the manner of this Superſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was according to the cuſtome of the <hi>Romans,</hi> who were wont either by written Titles, or by the voyce of the Cryer, to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie to the people the cauſe of the ſuffering of ſuch as were condemned: Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which cuſtome, <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> commanded this Title to be written, and faſtened to the Croſſe of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, manifeſting hereby unto the people the cauſe of his Condemnation. And as the <hi>Iewes</hi> were offended at Chriſt, ſo were they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152049:5"/> likewiſe at this Title. They ſue therefore unto <hi>Pilate,</hi> that it might be written: <hi>He called himſelfe the King of the Iewes.</hi> But becauſe they againſt <hi>Pilates</hi> wil had deſired <hi>Ieſus</hi> to be crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he againſt their wills ſets this Title on the Croſſe: and rather like Gods Officer, than <hi>Caeſars</hi> Friend, daſhes their petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, returning that anſwer wherewith hee was inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Quod ſcripſi, ſcripſi, What I have written, I have written,</hi> as though by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine infuſion hee had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied unto the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that he, whom they out of malicious cruelty had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152049:5"/> to be Crucified, was, is, and ever ſhall be <hi>[Ieſus of Nazareth, King of the Iewes.] Pilate</hi> herein ſeeks not ſo much our Saviours glory, as his owne excuſe: For now when his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence did accuſe him of this impious fact, and fearing a complaint might come againſt him unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for condemning ſuch, and ſo great a man with whom God was, without a legall Tryall, he fixes upon the Croſſe this Title, hoping to cleere himſelfe, that he crucified Chriſt not as the Sonne of God, or a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> but for that he was a ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152049:6"/> an enemy unto <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> one that affected both his Crowne and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. With this pretence hee thinkes to cloake his Injuſtice, becauſe he knew <hi>Caeſars</hi> Throne would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit no Rivall.</p>
                  <p>Whatſoever was <hi>Pilates</hi> Intendment, ſurely, it was the drift of the Holy Ghoſt, by this unjuſt Judge to vindicate the Juſt one, and to give him a Name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Names, and a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle above all Titles, which though Heaven and Earth paſſe away, yet ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for ever: For though the ſonnes of men are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to mortality, yet the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152049:6"/> Sonne of God ſhall endure unchangeably <hi>[Ieſus of Nazareth, King of the Iewes.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this Title wee are to conſider two things: The Manner, and the Matter. The manner how it was publiſhed: It was written: The matter, <hi>[Ieſus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth, King of the Iewes.]</hi> Firſt of the manner: The enſuing Verſe tells us, that it was written in <hi>Hebrew, Greeke,</hi> and <hi>Latine,</hi> the three moſt generall and famous Tongues in the world. The Reaſons wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (and that not without reaſon) are alleadged to be foure: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that all men
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152049:7"/> that underſtood any of theſe Languages, might know and conceive the cauſe of Chriſts ſuffering.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, that the Jewes perfidiouſneſſe might bee knowne to all Nations of what Language ſoever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, to ſignifie that Chriſt dyed for all, of what ſpeech, or Dialect ſoever they were.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, and laſtly, that every Tongue might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that <hi>[Ieſus of Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth is King of the Iewes.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>[And it was written.]</head>
                     <p>VVHatſoever is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, is written for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152049:7"/> our Inſtruction: whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is true in the generall, is not falſe in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. This Title of Chriſt affords us Inſtruction, yea, conſolation. <hi>Sampſon</hi> found Honey in the dead Lyon. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 14.8.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Judg.</hi> 14.8</note> The Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iuda,</hi> yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up his Ghoſt with a gracefull, diſgracefull Title over his Head, affoords each Chriſtian ſoule ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſurpaſſing the honey, or the Honey-combe. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve here how God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the malice of wicked men to the future benefit of his Church: their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is our advantage. The Jewes out of malice againſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152049:8"/> Chriſt, <hi>Pilate</hi> out of malice againſt the Jewes, deliver Chriſt with this Title, <hi>[Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus of Nazareth King of the Iewes.]</hi> What have the Jewes gained? what hath <hi>Pilate</hi> got hereby? The Jewes deſolation, <hi>Pilate</hi> Damnation: Onely the Church heereby reapes conſolation. Bleſſe wee with wonder the All-di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting providence of <hi>God,</hi> who of an enemy can make <hi>Pilate</hi> a benefit unto his people: Hee that can bring light out of darkenes, and good out of evill, can imploy the malice of his Adverſaries to the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall conſolation of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ones.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152049:8"/>
                     <head>[And it was written.]</head>
                     <p>LIttle did the Jewes; nay, little did <hi>Pilate</hi> thinke, that this act of his ſhould parralell Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: But now it is written: It is his owne hand that hath delivered it to Time, which ſhall preſerve it, ſo long as time ſhall bee. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve heere the juſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that Chriſt ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce againſt <hi>Pilate</hi> at the Day of Judgement, who pronounced an unjuſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt him, in the day of his Humiliation: For as <hi>Balſhazzar</hi> beheld the Hand-writing againſt him, upon the Walls of his Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152049:9"/> 
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.5. So ſhall Chriſt ſhew the hand-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>Pilate</hi> againſt him faſtned on his Croſſe; unto the Jewes he ſhall ſay, as to the wicked ſervant, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.22. <hi>Ex Ore tuo,</hi> Out of your owne mouthes wil I condemne you, yee wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Jewes; for yee cryed <hi>Crucifie him, Crucifie him:</hi> But unto <hi>Pilate</hi> he ſhall ſay; Thine owne hand is againſt thee, and ſhall condemne thee, O thou unjuſt Judge, for thou haſt written, <hi>[Ieſus of Nazareth, King of the Iewes.] Hae Tabulae te ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guunt, quas tu ſcripſiſt, hae te vinciri jabent.</hi> What needs any other Witneſſe?
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152049:9"/> Thine owne hand is againſt thy ſelfe: <hi>Iam pateris telis vulnera facta tuis.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>[And it was written.]</head>
                     <p>SEe here, <hi>The Son of God: The Holy one of Iſrael: The Everlaſting Father: The Prince of Peace: The wonderfull Councellor</hi> moſt ſhamefully expoſed to Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy, not with a paper on his backe, but with a Title of diſhonour over his head: For it was written, <hi>[Ieſus of Nazareth, King of the Iews.]</hi> Had theſe words beene ſpoken by <hi>Pilate,</hi> It had beene ſhame ſufficient, but to enlarge his reproach
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152049:10"/> they are written; yea, and written in Hebrew, Greek, and Latine, that ſo they might not be better known unto himſelfe, than to all the World. O curſed <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> that thus diſhonoureſt the Lord of Glory; the time will come, that thou ſhalt wiſh the Rocks to fall upon thee, and the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to cover thee from that face, which thou didſt ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> diſgracefully vilifie with a ſuppoſed Reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Title: O yee blood-thirſty <hi>Iewes,</hi> yee were of old termed a Stiffe-nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked people: Hath GOD ſent his Sonne in mercy? and doe you haſten him to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152049:10"/> the Croſſe in malice? Have you honoured in your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, <hi>Chriſtum venturum?</hi> Chriſt which was to come? And doe you now Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice upon the Croſſe <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum ventum</hi> Chriſt which is come? Oh hearts of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damant, is this the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement you give to the Meſſiah? The ſhame you doe unto him, ſhall binde ſhame to you, and your poſterity for ever.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>[And it was written.]</head>
                     <p>CHriſt, whoſe hands and heart were free from injury, is content to bee counted a Seducer; to bee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152049:11"/> judged a Traytor againſt <hi>Caeſar;</hi> to have an Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous Title over his head: Chriſt Ieſus, I ſay, the Lambe Immaculate, refuſes no ſhame, that hee might purchaſe Glory to his faithfull ones: Hee that was the God of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becomes the ſonne of ſhame: Hee that was the Righteous Redeemer, is deemed an unjuſt Uſurper: Hee that was the Lord of Life is condemned to Death: Hee that was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Angels, is now diſhonoured with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> He that was dignified with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152049:11"/> the Title, Holy, Holy, Holy, is heere diſgraced with a ſuppoſed Title of diſcredit <hi>[Ieſus of Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, King of the Iewes.] Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> ſhewes him diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to the people, with an <hi>Ecce Homo,</hi> as you may ſee verſe 5 of this Chap. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Man, Behold the Man: Pilate?</hi> yea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Redeemer of Man, in the ſhape of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant: <hi>Behold the Man?</hi> yea, behold him who was both God and Man: In compariſon of whoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe: In compariſon of whoſe Innocency: Both theſe in Angels are but ſtreames from his Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152049:12"/> Beames from his Brightneſſe, parcels from his Lumpe: Mutuations from his perfections.</p>
                     <p>Stand, O my Soule! and with admiration, bleſſe the Author of all Bleſſedneſſe, Chriſt, who to prevent thy ſhame, ſuſtained ſhame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, before his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>Cum ſceleratis nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus eſt:</hi> He was numbred among the wicked, for thy ſake: Hee was accounted ſinnefull, for thy ſalvation. <hi>Adam,</hi> by eating of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Tree, deprived thee of Life: Chriſt, by ſuffering on the curſed Tree, reſtores thee to Life.</p>
                     <p>Set to thy mouth then, O
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152049:12"/> my ſoule, and drinke hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily of this Life-giving Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: For <hi>Inveniſti in Cruce Gloriam:</hi> Chriſts Croſſe is thy comfort: His diſhonour is thy honour. That which is <hi>Ludibrium Impijs,</hi> is <hi>Miſterium Pijs:</hi> The Croſſe of Chiſt is to the <hi>Iewes</hi> a ſtumbling-blocke: To the Gentiles fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: But to thee, O my ſoule, it is the power of God, and the wiſedome of God. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 23.24.</p>
                     <p>Here then, O my Soule, exhilerate thy ſelfe in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the infinite goodneſſe of thy Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: Behold him inviro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned round about with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152049:13"/> On his right hand, <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> on his left hand, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience;</hi> below him, <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> above him, yea, above all, <hi>Charity,</hi> behold al theſe, and becauſe thou canſt not expreſſe, admire, with ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: And becauſe thou canſt not merit this, bleſſe with thankfulneſſe the bounty of him, whoſe Death is thy Life, whoſe ſhame is thy glory; even the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>But hath hee done this for thee? Then walk forth, O my ſoule, with courage, till thou meete the Croſſe: then take it up with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp; beare it in deſpight of thy Saviours enemies:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152049:13"/> Follow thy Redeemer, with a Croſſe at thy backe, and ſay with St. <hi>Paul Gal.</hi> 9.14. <hi>God forbid, that I ſhould glory in anything, but in the Croſſe of Chriſt, whereby the world is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified unto me, and I unto the World:</hi> For <hi>Crux Chriſti,</hi> is <hi>Lux Chriſtiani:</hi> The Croſſe of Chriſt, is the glory of a Chriſtian, which Croſſe hath freed thee from the blindneſſe of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror; reſtored thee to reſt, overcame Hell for thee: brought thee neere unto God, opened the gate of Heaven; wrought thy peace, and purchaſt ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happines unto thee.</p>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:152049:14"/>
                     <p>Honour him, then O my ſoule, who for thee was diſhonoured: Suffer a little miſery for him, in this World, who ſuffered, and endured a World of Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for thee: Entitle him in thy heart; who bare this Title over his head <hi>[Ieſus of Nazareth King of the Iewes.]</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And ſo from the manner I paſſe to the matter of this Inſcription.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:152049:61"/>
                  <head>[IESUS OF NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZARETH, KING OF THE JEWES.]</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N which words, are contayned the cauſes (as they would have it) of our Saviours Condemnation: In the writing whereof, rather GODS Will, than <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates,</hi> did appeare: For in this Title, are contayned three Divine reaſons, why Chriſt, the onely begotten Sonne of GOD, ſhould
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152049:62"/> yeeld up his life upon the Croſſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, becauſe hee was <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, becauſe he was <hi>Nazarenus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, becauſe hee was <hi>Rex Iudaeorum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He was <hi>Ieſus,</hi> that is, <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator,</hi> A Saviour: Hee was <hi>Nazarenus,</hi> that is, <hi>Floridus,</hi> A Flower, or flouriſhing. He was <hi>Rex Iudaeorum,</hi> that is <hi>Rex Confitentium,</hi> King of the Jewes, not carnally, but ſpiritually, not by Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, but by Faith: King of thoſe, who doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve with the heart, and confeſſe him with the mouth, to bee the true
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152049:62"/> 
                     <hi>Meſsiah. Pilate</hi> was blinde, and could not ſee this: The Jewes were obſtinate, and would not know this: But now it is revealed to Babes and ſucklings, by Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; for all, that are borne of God, know, that by nature, they were ſinnes ſubjects, yet here they finde Him <hi>Ieſum</hi> a Saviour: By nature, they are ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Noſtrils of God, yet heere they finde him <hi>Nazarenum,</hi> A ſweet ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Flower: By Nature, they are Satans Bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaves; yet, for their Redemption, they finde him heere, <hi>Regem Iudae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum,</hi> King of all thoſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152049:63"/> that confeſſe his name. This Title of Chriſt was written (as I ſaid before) in <hi>Hebrew, Greeke,</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine:</hi> The <hi>Hebrewes</hi> had the true Prieſt-hood: The <hi>Grecians</hi> abounded in Wiſedome; And the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> in Dominion, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: The firſt, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed Chriſt to bee the true Prieſt; the ſecond, to be the wiſeſt Prophet; the third, to be the Potentſt King. Here then is <hi>Chriſts Sacerdotall Office,</hi> in that hee is <hi>Ieſus.</hi> His Propheticall, in that he is <hi>Nazarenus.</hi> His Regal, in that he is <hi>Rex Iudaeorum,</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>Of theſe in Order.</l>
                        <l>Firſt he is <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:152049:63"/>
                     <head>[Ieſus.]</head>
                     <p>THis Name includes the firſt reaſon: Why our Saviour dyed upon the Croſſe: Our firſt Parents, by eating the forbidden fruit, offended chiefly in three things. In Pride, in diſobedience, and in Carnall delight. Pride, in aſpiring to bee like their maker; Diſobedience, in tranſgreſſing the Law of their maker. Carnall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, in preferring the pleaſantneſſe of the fruit, before the love of their Maker. But ſeeing Chriſt came into the World to be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152049:64"/> a Saviour, hee muſt ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie for man, by contrary meanes: For Pride, by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; for Diſobedience, by Obedience, for carnall delight, by ſuffering of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; theſe three Chriſt performed. Looke into the 2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 8. and there St. <hi>Paul</hi> make it playnely appeare, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was not behinde hand in any of theſe: Hee humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe (ſaith the Apoſtle,) behold his true Humility: and became obedient, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his prompt Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; unto Death, even the death of the Croſſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the largeneſſe of his puniſhment. So that if
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152049:64"/> Chriſt will be a Saviour, hee muſt, by the death of the Croſſe, <hi>open the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven to all Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This was typified in the Old Teſtament, by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing of <hi>Iſaak:</hi> By the lifting up of the Brazen Serpent: By the ſmiting of the Rocke: By the Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Oblations, and Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings: And yet, theſe hard-hearted Jews could not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it.</p>
                     <p>O fooliſh <hi>Pilate,</hi> thinkeſt thou to diſhonour the Son of the moſt High, by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Ieſus?</hi> No, it was a name aſſigned unto him from Heaven for the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152049:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaid unto <hi>Ioſeph, Math.</hi> 1.29. <hi>Thou ſhalt call his name Ieſus; for he ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes.</hi> It is that name, wherein Chriſt moſt glories, and whereof, every Chriſtian is leaſt aſhamed.</p>
                     <p>Seeing there is no name under heaven whereby we can be ſaved, but by the name of Jeſus. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12.</note> A bleſſed name, a ſweete name: <hi>Mel in ore, Melos in aure, Iubilus in Corde,</hi> (as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſweetly ſaith) <hi>Honey in the mouth, Melody in the eare, But a Iubile, a ioy in the heart.</hi> This name, is light unto the ſoule. <hi>Yee were Darkneſſe,</hi> ſaies the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152049:65"/> Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.8. <hi>but now yee are light in the Lord.</hi> This name gives health to the body. <hi>In the name of Ieſus of Nazareth, riſe up, and walke, Acts</hi> 3.6. This Name is the Life, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, the reſtauration of the ſoule of a Chriſtian. <hi>Aridus eſt omnis cibus, ſi non oleo iſto infunditur, inſipidus, ſi non hoc ſale conditur,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">St. Bern.</note> (ſaith St. <hi>Bernard) All Spirituall foode is dry, if this Oyle bee not powred into it; unſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, if it be not ſeaſoned with this Salt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Other names of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are names of Majeſty, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this is a name of mercy: To bee called the Word,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152049:66"/> the Sonne, the Annointed of God: Theſe Titles pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime Chriſts Glory: but the Name of <hi>Ieſus</hi> imports our Redemption. By the former, we know him to be God, by the latter, wee know him to be our Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, and Saviour: To him then, and to him onely, properly, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs the Name <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But it may be objected, that there are others, in the Scripture, called after the ſame Name: As <hi>Ieſus,</hi> or <hi>Iehoſcua,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nun: Ieſus,</hi> or <hi>Iehoſcua,</hi> the High-Prieſt of the Jewes: And <hi>Ieſus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Sirach,</hi> the Author of the Booke
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152049:66"/> called <hi>Eccleſiaſticus.</hi> All this I confeſſe, and I know, that the firſt was famous for his valour, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> the ſecond, for his Integrity in his Preiſthood: the third, for his Wiſedome and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. But alas, theſe three were but types of our Jeſus. The firſt repreſented his Kingly, the ſecond his Preiſtly, the third his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall Office: They were ſo tearmed in regard of ſome temporall and particular Deliverances: Our Jeſus ſo ſtyled, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of that generall and Spirituall Redemption, which hee hath wrought
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152049:67"/> for all his Saints, Jewes, and Gentiles. The former were ſent before, like <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaes</hi> ſtaffe, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.29.<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.29.</note> but could not raiſe Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde from the dead. But the true and powerfull <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> was faine to deſcend from Heaven himſelfe, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> from Mount <hi>Carmel,</hi> to apply his mouth, to our mouthes, his eyes, to our eyes, his hands, to our hands, becomming the ſame with us, in ſubſtance, in Nature, and infirmity, (ſinne onely excepted) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee could bee raiſed. <hi>Magna miſeria ſuperbus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo: Maior miſericordia hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milis Deus,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">St. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                        </note> (ſaith St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.)
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152049:67"/> Great miſery it was, to ſee man ſo proud, greater mercy, to ſee God ſo humble.</hi> And therefore to him pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, and to none but him, belongs that Name, which is above all Names, the Name of <hi>Ieſus:</hi> For hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is the Saviour of the World, to whom both the Name, and Office ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaines. And as he is by Name, <hi>Ieſus,</hi> ſo is hee by Nature, a Saviour. For him alone does the Goſpell proclaime throughout all Ages to be a Saviour: by whom <hi>Abraham</hi> was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted righteous. Hee was that Salvation which the Patriarchs deſired; he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152049:68"/> was that Salvation, which the Ceremoniall Law pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured; he was that Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which the Prophets foretold; he was that Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which <hi>Iacob</hi> waited for, when he ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.18. <hi>I have waited for thy Salvation O Lord.</hi> He was that Salvation that <hi>David</hi> prayed for, hee was that Salvation which old <hi>Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> rejoyced in, when hee ſung, <hi>Mine eyes have ſeene thy Salvation. Luke</hi> 2.30. This was that Salvation, by which the Patriarchs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into Heaven, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets attained bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the Saints en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy true happineſſe. In him
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152049:68"/> alone were all the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the <hi>Meſsiah</hi> fully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed: Hee alone trod the Wine-preſſe of Gods wrath: He alone ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied his Fathers Juſtice: He alone became <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the price of our Redemption. It was he, that was ſent of the Father, to ſave the World. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.17. And for this cauſe, he came him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into the world, to ſave ſinners. It was hee that was ſmitten for us: <hi>Propter ſcelus populi mei percuſſi eum: I have ſmitten him for the wickedneſſe of my people: Traditus eſt in mortem propter offenſas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras: Hee was delivered
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152049:69"/> to death for our offences. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Chriſtus ſine peccato, pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati paenam ſubire dignatus eſt,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">St. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                        </note> (ſaith St. <hi>Aug.</hi>) Hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, without ſinne, was pleaſed to undergoe the puniſhment for ſinne: His Death was not for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but for us. <hi>Quaſi pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator occiſus eſt, ut pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores juſtificarentur apud Deum,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">St. Ambr.</note> (ſaith <hi>St. Ambroſe) Hee was ſlaine as a ſinner, that ſinners might be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before God.</hi> It was our ſinnes, not his owne deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, that faſtened him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſſe. <hi>Pro me do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit, qui nihil habuit, quod pro ſe doleret</hi> (ſayes the ſame Father.) God was the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152049:69"/> Creditor, Man was the Debtor; but he that was both God, and Man, the Pay-maſter. Thus he, who enjoyed the Name of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> hath performed the Office, and remaineth our alone Saviour: Bleſſed in his Name, and for ever bleſſed in his Perſon.</p>
                     <p>I have long inſiſted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ſweet Name, for that it brings ſo much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit unto us: yet can I not ſhake hands with our <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Adverſaries, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe ſo much unto the Name, and ſo little unto the perſon of <hi>Ieſus.</hi> They affirme, that the bare Name it ſelfe being uſed,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152049:70"/> hath great power, and doth drive away Devi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, though the perſon, that uſeth it, be voide of good affection: whereas indeed, the Devill is no more timerous of the Name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> than of any other Title of God. The ſonnes of <hi>Sceva, Act.</hi> 19.14 found this to be true, by their owne deare experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for they could not adjure the evill ſpirit, though they uſed the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> whom <hi>Paul</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. And as they aſcribe too much to the Name: ſo they aſcribe too little to the Perſon of <hi>Ieſus:</hi> in that they make him but a <hi>Demi-Saviour,</hi> joyning others
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152049:70"/> with him, as partners in the worke of our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, coupling our workes, with his Merits, our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, with his ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: The interceſſion of Saints, with his Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; eſpecially, the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> whom they call, <hi>the Queen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of Heaven, the Mother of Grace;</hi> requeſting her, that by the authority of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhee would command her ſonne. Oh take heede of ſharing ſtakes betweene Chriſt, and any creature in the act of our ſalvation. He will not bee accounted joynt purchaſer of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption with any, no not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152049:71"/> with his owne Mother, the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> for hee was her Saviour, as well as ours: <hi>My Spirit reioyceth in God my Saviour,</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>Luke</hi> 1.47.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.47.</note> And <hi>Sanguinem, quem de Matre accepit, pro Matre obtulit,</hi> (ſaith one of the Fathers) <hi>The Blood, which hee receiued from his Mother, hee ſhed for his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let us acknowledge our ſelves loſt by Nature, but found onely by Chriſt. He onely it was, that came to ſeeke, and to ſave that which was loſt: We were, through <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, bound by the Divel, wee are loſed onely by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152049:71"/> 
                        <hi>Chriſts</hi> Paſſion, <hi>Alligavit fortem, vinculis Paſsionis.</hi> It is hee, that bound the ſtrong man, &amp; ſpoyled him of his weapons: It was hee that ſet us at liberty, when we were in bondage: That found us, when wee were loſt: That called us home, when wee were baniſhed: That raiſed us, when wee were dead; that redeemed us, when wee were miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable captives; he reſtored our lives, by loſing his owne; he unbound us, by faſtning himſelfe; he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came, by being overcome; he redeemed us, by enthra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling himſelfe; he cured us, by his owne wounds;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152049:72"/> raiſed us to life, by his owne Death; made us rich, by his owne poverty; robbed himſelfe of his dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, by becomming a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; of his Royalty, by paying of tribute; of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, by becomming a ſervant; of his credit, for he was blaſphemed; of his joy, for hee was heavy to the Death; of his wel-fare, for hee was wounded, ſcourged, nayled, crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and all this, for our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. What Saint, or Angel did? Nay, what Saint or Angel could doe the like for us? He one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and alone, <hi>Carnem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, pro omnium Carne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendit,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152049:72"/> &amp; animam ſuam pro omnium anima conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Saint Cyril</hi>
                        <note place="margin">St. <hi>Cyril.</hi>
                        </note>) <hi>He,</hi> (I ſay) <hi>payned his fleſh, for the fleſh of us all, his ſoule, for all our ſoules.</hi> Hee was <hi>Moſes</hi> Serpent to heale us, Gods Lambe, to feed us with his fleſh, and cloath us with his fleece: The true Pelican, nouriſhing us with his blood. <hi>O profunditas Divitiarum! O the depth of the riches of the mercy of this our</hi> Jeſus! Let us draw waters of comfort out of this depth of Mercy: Let us not reſt contented with that generall name of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians;</hi> but labour for aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſalvation, that as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152049:73"/> 
                        <hi>Thomas</hi> called Chriſt his Lord, and his God: <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20 28. ſo we may, by faith, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one particularly, call him, <hi>Our Jeſus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>We are all naturally like the wounded man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Jeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho: Luke</hi> 10.30.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luke</hi> 10.30.</note> Let us ſeeke out that good <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan,</hi> who hath compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on us, will binde up our wounds, powre Wine and Oyle into them, and reſtore us to health.</p>
                     <p>Sinne is an unſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table load, with it we are all over-burthened; yet our Jeſus calls us, <hi>Come unto me all yee that are weary, and heavy laden, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152049:73"/> you. Math.</hi> 11.28. He invites gratiouſly, let us haſten ſpeedily; <hi>Non pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſed affectibus; Not with our feet, but with our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> Whilſt he ſtandeth at the doore, and knocks, let us open unto him, leſt by too long delay wee loſe him: Then ſhall wee open the doore, but hee hath withdrawne himſelfe: then ſhall we ſeeke him, but not finde him; call him, but he will not anſwere: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore while the time ſerves, let us ſay unto our <hi>Ieſus,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> to the Lord, <hi>Say unto my Soule, I am thy Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> If we aske in time, we ſhall receive: If wee
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152049:74"/> ſeeke in time, we ſhall find; if we knocke in time, hee will open unto us; if wee beleeve, we ſhall be ſaved. Away then with all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite of our owne merit, or the Holineſſe of any Saint: Let <hi>Chriſt</hi> be the ſole Lord of our ſalvation, without any Copartner; for hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone hath poſſeſſion of that three-fold Treaſury, which muſt make us rich unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: namely, the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Glory, the Treaſure of Grace, and the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Wiſedome. Man was exiled from Celeſtiall Glory, Chriſt alone en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the Treaſury of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that hee might bring
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152049:74"/> Mankind unto Glory. Man was an enemy unto God; therefore Chriſt had the Treaſury of Grace, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile man unto God. Man was blind, and wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in darkneſſe; therefore Chriſt had the Treaſury of Wiſedome, to teach men the way to eternall Life. Looke in <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.14.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14.</note> and you ſhall finde all theſe three comprehended in one Verſe: <hi>Spectavimus glorian, plenam gratia &amp; veritatis. We ſaw the glory of Chriſt, behold the firſt: full of Grace, behold the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: and Truth, behold the third:</hi> Now therefore let us ſay, <hi>Non nobis Domine,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152049:75"/> non nobis, ſed Nomini tuo da gloriam. Not unto us Lord, not unto us, but unto thy Name give the glory.</hi> For thou O <hi>Ieſus,</hi> art made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us of God, by thy paines ſuſtained, Wiſdome, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, Sanctification, and Redemption.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore, ſeeing that thou my bleſſed Saviour, haſt borne my ſorrows, ſhed my teares, ſuffered my diſgrace, ſuſtained my puniſhment, and payd my Debt, let <hi>Iewes, Turkes,</hi> and <hi>Heathen</hi> revile thee, I will honour thee: let them blaſpheme the Name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> I will adore it; let them perſecute it, I will
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152049:75"/> make it my refuge: for the Name of the Lord, is a ſtrong tower of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: They, that flye unto it, are ſecured. Let them diſdaine it, I ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme it to bee a precious oyntment powred out; let them vilifie it, I will glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in it: For with the Lord, there is Iuſtice, but with our <hi>Ieſus,</hi> there is plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Redemption.</p>
                     <p>O Lord, what <hi>Pylate</hi> deemed to bee thy ſhame, proves to bee thy glory: Hee writes thee diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <hi>Ieſus</hi> with his hand, whom hee would not call faithfully <hi>Ieſus</hi> with his heart. Yet this is thy
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152049:76"/> Name, this is thy function: <hi>Ieſus,</hi> by Title, a Saviour by Office. With this name <hi>Ieſus,</hi> thy Birth was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, and with this Name <hi>Ieſus,</hi> thy Death is honoured: What thou broughteſt into the world, by the Angels Direction, thou carryedſt out of the world, by <hi>Pilates</hi> Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth King of the Iewes.</hi> And ſo I paſſe from his Name <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> unto his Title <hi>Nazare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> of <hi>Nazareth.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:152049:76"/>
                     <head>[Nazareth.]</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>NAzareth</hi> was the name of that Towne, which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> dwelt in, when hee returned out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the which <hi>Ieſus</hi> continued, until hee undertooke the Propheticall, and Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotall functions: From which Towne he received this Title, to be called <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarenus, Ieſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth.</hi> This then is a Title given unto <hi>Ieſus,</hi> taken from the Towne, or Village, where the Angell <hi>Gabriel</hi> brought the meſſage unto <hi>Mary,</hi> and where Chriſt dwelt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his returne from <hi>Egypt:</hi>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:152049:77"/> and not from the order, and Votary of <hi>Nazarites,</hi> as ſome doe vainely ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine. Neither is this Title without a Myſtery: For this word <hi>Nazarenus</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies three things: <hi>Sanctified, Separated,</hi> and <hi>a Flower.</hi> In all which ſences, <hi>Ieſus</hi> may be truely tearmed <hi>Nazare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Firſt, hee was <hi>ſanctified,</hi> not imperfectly, and in part, but perfectly, and in whole: And this was not, by any external meanes, after his Birth, but onely by the Holy Ghoſt, in his conception. And therefore he was <hi>ſanctified in utero, in the wombe;</hi> and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152049:77"/> 
                        <hi>ex utero, Out of the wombe.</hi> Hee was <hi>ſanctified</hi> in the wombe: the which <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> hath two parts.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, the stoppage in the propagation of Originall ſin, and of the guilt of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion: which, becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> was from <hi>Adam,</hi> as from a Root; and not by <hi>Adam,</hi> as by a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is not derived unto him: For man is originally ſinfull, not becauſe of his ſubſtance, but becauſe of his Generation, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from a ſinfull man. For God, at the beginning, ſet downe this Order, that what evill <hi>Adam</hi> had brought upon himſelfe, he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152049:78"/> ſhould derive the ſame to every one of his poſterity, begotten by man. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when any Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets a Child, he conveyes into it, beſides humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the corruption of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature. <hi>Chriſt</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for the preventing of this, was not begotten by Man, but conceived <hi>modo ineffabili,</hi> by the Holy Ghoſt: That ſo hee might take the ſubſtance of the Virgin, without the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of that ſubſtance.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond part of this <hi>Sanctification,</hi> which is <hi>ex utero, Out of the wombe,</hi> is the perfect endowing of the Manhood of Chriſt,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152049:78"/> with all pureneſſe, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, to make him a meete Mediatour. Hee was <hi>ſanctified</hi> out of the wombe, for his whole Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature was full of Grace and Truth. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.14 Full of Grace in his works, full of Truth in his words. Holy in his Birth, holy in his Life, and holy in his Death.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, as he was <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarenus ſanctified:</hi> ſo is he <hi>Nazarenus ſeparated.</hi> He was that Scape-goat, ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from his fellows, to make an Attonement for the ſinnes of the World.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Lev.</hi> 16.10</note> He was ſeperated from his Fathers Court of Majeſty,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152049:79"/> by taking upon him the forme of a Servant. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7.</note> He was ſeparated from his owne Nation, when he fled into <hi>Egypt</hi> for feare of <hi>Herod.</hi> He was ſeparated from his Brethren, and Kinsfolke, to doe his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Will: Hee was ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from his Diſciples, when he was hanging upon the Croſſe. Hee was ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Living, when he dyed for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. Hee was ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the World, when hee aſcended into Heaven. And thus was <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> tearmed <hi>Nazarenus,</hi> that is, <hi>Separated.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thirdly, <hi>Ieſus</hi> is <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renus:</hi>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:152049:79"/> That is, <hi>Flos,</hi> or <hi>floridus, A Flower,</hi> or <hi>flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing:</hi> for ſo is is hee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. <hi>Eſay</hi> 11. <hi>There ſhall come a Rod out of the ſtemme of</hi> Jeſſe, <hi>and a branch;</hi> or as the Vulgar Tranſlation hath it, <hi>Flos de radice ejus aſcendet. A Flower ſhall grow out of his roote.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chriſt is more ſpecially called <hi>Nazarenus,</hi> a <hi>flower,</hi> becauſe, as <hi>Protagoras</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, Flowers <hi>Solem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent in Coelo Patrem, Solum in terra Matrem:</hi> That is, <hi>Flowers have the Sunne in the Heavens for their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the ſoyle on the earth for their Mother.</hi> So <hi>Ieſus,</hi> the Flower out of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152049:80"/> 
                        <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> had in Heaven a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without a Mother, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his God-head: And in Earth, a Mother, without a Father, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Manhood. As he was God, not differing from the Father; but <hi>ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per apud Patrem, ſemper cum Patre, temper de Patre, ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in Patre. Alwayes by the Father, alwayes with the Father, alwayes of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and alwayes in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Even ſo, as he was Man, he was <hi>Homo de homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, propter hominem, ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum hominem, ſuper homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. He was Man of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind according to his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, Man for mankind
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152049:80"/> in regard of our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his, Man, according to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, in regard of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; Man, above mankind, in regard of his Holineſſe. Sine quo, Pater nunquam fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, ſine quo, Mater nunquam fuiſset. Without whom, the Father never was, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom, the Mother never had beene.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ieſus</hi> is called here <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarenus,</hi> a <hi>Flower;</hi> Firſt, becauſe of the ſweetneſſe that is in him. Secondly, becauſe of the ſweetneſſe he is to us. That ſweetneſſe, which is in him, is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed two wayes.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, in the ſweetneſſe of his Vertues, manifeſted
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152049:81"/> in his holy converſation, wherein hee was a ſweete-ſmelling <hi>Flower</hi> for imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, he was a ſweet ſmelling <hi>Flower</hi> in his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, when hee <hi>offered himſelfe to God, a Sacrifice of a ſweete ſmelling ſavour, for our Reconciliation. Eph.</hi> 5.2.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.2.</note> Laſtly, he is the hope of that eternall ſweetneſſe, which we ſhal enjoy here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, in the Kingdome of Heaven. For <hi>Dedit Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem in terra, praetium noſtrae Redemptionis, ſed ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat Divinitatem in Coelo, praemium noſtrae glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis. Hee gave his Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon the Earth, the price
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152049:81"/> of our Redemption, but doth reſerve his Deity in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the reward of our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There are five principall Flowers in uſe with us,<note place="margin">Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to five ſorts of Flowers:</note> whereunto this our <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renus,</hi> this our <hi>Ieſus,</hi> may bee fitly compared: The <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                        <hi>Violet,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Violet.</note> the <hi>Lilly,</hi> the <hi>Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron.</hi> the <hi>Roſe,</hi> and the <hi>Marygold.</hi> The <hi>Violet</hi> (you know) is little in quantity, low in growth, not raiſed farre from the earth: ſignifying hereby, the Humility of our <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renus,</hi> the Lowlineſſe of our Redeemer. The which Humility of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> was manifeſted in three parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152049:82"/> 
                        <hi>Naſcendo,</hi> In his Birth: <hi>Vivendo,</hi> In his life: <hi>Morien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o,</hi> In his death. In his Birth, he was humble: For being the Creator of all things, be diſdained not to become a Creature. <hi>Factor terrae, factus in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra; Creator Coeli, creatus ſub Coelo.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">St. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                        </note> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſt.) Hee, that made the Earth, was borne upon the Earth: Hee, that created the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, was made under the Heavens.</hi> He choſe not to be the Son of ſome Great Empreſſe, but of <hi>Mary,</hi> a poore Virgin in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Hee was not borne in a Princely Palace, but in a Stable, not layd in a curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152049:82"/> coſtly Cradle, but in a ſilly Cratch. Not atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on by Knights, &amp; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates, but by Oxen, and Aſſes, and ſuch like crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Such was our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Humility in his birth.</p>
                     <p>In his Life: He was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to worke at the Trade of his ſuppoſed Father <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> not affecting Lands, Houſes, nor poſſeſſions: <hi>For the Foxes had holes, &amp; the Birds of the Ayre had neſts, but the Son of Man had not where to lay his Head.</hi> Not abounding in worldly Treaſure; for the Fiſh of the Sea muſt pay Tribute unto <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Not ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly aſpiring unto Rule,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152049:83"/> and Government; for when the people would have made him King, he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, and conveyed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e from among them: ſuch was our Saviours Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility in his Life.</p>
                     <p>In his Death, he ſuffered himſelfe to bee ſcourged, ſpit on, blaſphemed, crown'd with Thornes, and condemn'd by an unjuſt Judge. Laſtly, when hee was nayled moſt cruelly upon the Croſſe, and made a ſpectacle of diſgrace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all beholders, and had ſuſtained the utmoſt of the Jewiſh malice, yet hee prayed for his enemies, ſaying, <hi>Father, forgive
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152049:83"/> them, for they know not what they doe. Luke</hi> 23.34. Such was our Saviours Humility in his Death.</p>
                     <p>This Humility of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is recorded by Saint <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 2.6.7. where he ſayes of him, <hi>That being in the forme of God, he thought it no robbery, to bee equall with God: And yet he made himſelfe of no reputation, but tooke upon him the ſhape of a ſervant: and humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and became obedient to Death, even the death of the Croſſe.</hi> This Humility of our Saviour is expoſed by himſelfe to us, for our imitation: <hi>Learne of me, for I am meeke, and humble in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152049:84"/> heart. Math.</hi> 11.29. And thus is <hi>Chriſt</hi> compared to a <hi>Violet,</hi> and may be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Nazarenus, The Flower of Humility.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſecond Flower, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> whereunto our <hi>Nazarenus</hi> is compared, is the <hi>Lilly:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Lillie.</note> a Flower growing upon a ſtraight ſtalke, raiſed from the Earth; white of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and of a fragrant ſmell, ſignifying unto us <hi>the innocency of our bleſſed Saviour. Ego ſum Lilium Convallium:</hi> You know whoſe ſpeech it is. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.1. <hi>I am the Lilly of the Valleys.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Ancients were wont tom Emblematize Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152049:84"/> by Whiteneſſe, which is the moſt pure, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect colour. And ſo the Ancient of Dayes, is ſayd to have his Garments white as ſnow. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.14. And well may he be called a <hi>Lilly,</hi> for his Whiteneſſe; well may hee be ſtyled a Lambe, for his Innocency. <hi>Ecce Agnus Dei, qui tollit peccata mundi. Behold the Lambe of God, that takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſinnes of the World. Iohn</hi> 1.29. whole Hands, Heart, and Tongue, were free from injury. O Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Innocency! who offended neither in <hi>thought word,</hi> nor <hi>deed,</hi> being nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſobedient to God,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152049:85" rendition="simple:additions"/> nor injurious to men; but full of Grace towards God, and of Truth towards men. <hi>Moſes</hi> led not the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> into <hi>Canaan,</hi> but <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nun,</hi> becauſe he offended not at the waters of ſtrife: No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting unto us, that hee, who was to be the Saviour of the World, and the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the ſpirituall <hi>Iſrael,</hi> into the Celeſtiall <hi>Canaan,</hi> muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In Nature, our <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> was like other men: but in Holineſſe of Nature, tranſcending all men. In all things like us, ſinne onely excepted. He
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152049:25"/> was <hi>Noſtri generis ſocius, ſed noſtrae contaminationis alienus. Like us in Nature, but not like unto us in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Nature.</hi> Great was the commendation, which was due, by merit unto <hi>Cato,</hi> and <hi>Fabritius,</hi> two noble <hi>Romans,</hi> famous for their Uprightneſſe, and Integrity. Singular was the Innocency of <hi>Samuel,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Recorded 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 3.</note> approved by the ſuffrages of all <hi>Iſrael;</hi> who defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or oppreſſed no man: who had neither taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way any mans Oxe, or Aſſe, nor had blinded his eyes with the bribes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y one. The Integrity of theſe Worthies, reaches
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152049:26"/> but to men: but the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of our Saviour, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it ſelfe farther, even to the Law of God, which he violated not in the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt thing, in the leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. This made him bold to demand of the <hi>Iewes, Ioh.</hi> 8.46. <hi>Qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ex vobis arguet me de peccato? Which of you can convince me of ſin?</hi> He was holy in his cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, upright in his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, divine in his words, juſt in his workes: Free from Originall, free from Actuall ſinne; neither o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting good, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting evill; ſanctified in his Conception, holy in his Birth, innocent in his
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152049:26"/> Life, and righteous at his Death.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Adam</hi> was innocent at his Creation, but his Whiteneſſe was ſoone ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed, and changed into Blackneſſe. But in our <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarenus,</hi> was no inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Satan could worke upon: And therefore hee ſayes, <hi>The Prince of this World commeth, but he finds nothing in me.</hi> So immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table was his Purity, ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable his Innocency, as could neither, by the World, nor the Devill, nor by any other meanes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſtayned, or polluted. What was his whole Life? The Modell of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152049:27"/> a Glaſſe of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, yeelding to his Parents, Duty, and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: Giving bread to the hungry, ſight to the blind, hearing to the deafe, feete to the lame, health to the ſicke, life to the dead, comfort to the ſorrowfull, forgiveneſſe to the ſinner; rendring unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that which was <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and unto God, that which was Gods. Heere was Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence ſo ſpotleſſe, as that it was approved from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by the voyce of God himſelfe: <hi>This is my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Sonne, in whom I am wel pleaſed. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>h.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Math.</hi> 3.</note> the laſt Verſe. It was cleered by
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152049:27"/> 
                        <hi>Pilate</hi> too, though an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Judge; <hi>I finde no fault in this man. Luk.</hi> 23.14. It was confeſſed by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting. Thiefe upon the Croſſe, in the ſame <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, verſ.</hi> 41. <hi>This man hath done nothing amiſſe:</hi> Thus is <hi>Chriſt</hi> compared to the <hi>Lilly,</hi> for his Whiteneſſe, and may juſtly bee called <hi>Nazarenus, The Flower of Innocency.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The third Flower, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> our <hi>Nazarenus</hi> may be compared, is the <hi>Saffron,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron.</note> which is a Flower, (as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> obſerves) uſed in making of Sawce for Meate,<note place="margin">St. <hi>Bern.</hi>
                        </note> or in ſeaſoning ſome kind of Diſhes, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152049:28"/> does repreſent Abſtinence, or Temperance, which may very fitly figure out unto us, the Temperance of our <hi>Nazarenus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When firſt hee ſet foote into his Propheticall Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and began to make himſelfe knowne to the World, hee entred with admirable Abſtinence, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting miraculouſly, Forty dayes, and Forty nights. <hi>Math.</hi> 4.2. Profane <hi>Eſau</hi> ſold his Birth-right for a meſſe of pottage, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.32. and was the picture of a Belly-god: But to ſhew that the Kingdome of God did not conſiſt in meates, and drinkes, as our Apoſt.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152049:28"/> ſayes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17.</note> 
                        <hi>Chriſt</hi> beginneth with Faſting, and continues in Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which is, a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate uſe of meate, and drinke, unto the end. Not, like many <hi>Diveſtes,</hi> who fare delicately every day, turning faſting, into fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, making their guts, a Gulfe of pleaſure, and their Belly, their God; drawing all their Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe downe their throats. He who was God, of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, and had all things at command, who opens his hand, and filleth all things living with plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, was pleaſed to uſe ſparingly, that which
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152049:29"/> others ſpent prodigally; and to ſave that by Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, which others ſpoile by Luxury: And thus is <hi>Chriſt</hi> compared to the <hi>Saffron,</hi> and may be fitly called <hi>Nazarenus, The Flower of Temperance.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth Flower, whereunto our <hi>Nazarenus</hi> may be compared, is the <hi>Roſe,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Roſe.</note> the moſt noble of all Flowers; dilating it ſelfe abroad, and of a ruddy colour, which properly repreſents <hi>Chriſt,</hi> our <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarenus. Ego ſum Roſa Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronis.</hi> Cant. 2.1. <hi>I am the Roſe of Sharon.</hi> He is firſt, like the Roſe in his dilata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſpreading him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152049:29"/> abroad, ſeeking not onely the loſt ſheepe of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> but every ſheepe that hath ſtrayed from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Fold. <hi>Num Iudaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Deus ſolum? non &amp; Gentium?</hi> is the Apoſtles Queſtion: <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.29.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.29.</note> Yea, of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo. For us hath hee called, which were of the <hi>Gentiles, who ſometimes were a farre off, are now made nigh, by the blood of Chriſt. Eph.</hi> 2.13. Secondly, hee is like the <hi>Roſe</hi> in colour, <hi>Rubicundus, Red,</hi> with his owne blood. His colour was fore-told by the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> 63.2. <hi>Why is thy Apparrell red, and thy Garments like him
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152049:30"/> that treadeth the Wine-preſſe?</hi> The Redneſſe of this <hi>Roſe</hi> preſents to our ſent, the Charity of our <hi>Nazarenus. Contendunt Paſsio, &amp; Charitas: illa, ut plus ardeat, iſta, ut plu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">St. Bern.</note> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſweetly: <hi>There was a holy contention betwixt his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and his Charity, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one ſhould excell in redneſſe of blood, or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in fervency of affection.</hi> His Charity enlarged his Paſſion; for if hee had not loved, he would not have ſuffered; and the Redneſſe of his Paſſion, diſcovered the fervour of his Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:152049:30"/>
                     <p>Wee read in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that our Saviour was ſixe times dyed in blood, that thereby he might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell the <hi>Roſe</hi> in Redneſſe.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, in his Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: then was this <hi>Roſe</hi> at his firſt budding, ſprinkled with Blood, whilſt he was yet nouriſhed with the milke of his Mothers paps.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, in the Garden, when in that great conflict, between the infirme fleſh, and the prompt Spirit, he ſweat <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Clods of water and blood,</hi> falling downe to the ground.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, when hee was faſtened unto a Pillar, and his ſacred body made all
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152049:31"/> red with ſcourgings.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, when the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers harrowed his holy Head, with a Crowne of Thornes.</p>
                     <p>Fiftly, when they nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his innocent Hands, and Feete unto the Croſſe.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, when his precious ſide was pierced with a Speare, there appeared a Fountaine, out of which flowed Water, and Blood. Thus was our <hi>white Lilly</hi> changed into a <hi>red Roſe,</hi> red in Blood, and red in Charity.</p>
                     <p>Thou, <hi>O Saviour,</hi> once didſt affirme, that no man had greater Charity, than to lay downe his life for
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152049:31"/> his friend. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſe</hi> 13.</note> How is this true? Hadſt not thou greater Charity, when thou didſt lay downe thy Life for thine Enemies? yea ſurely; but thou, in thy Nature, wert more than Man, and in thy Charity, no leſſe than God. Never any Charity like that of thine, which being God, didſt dye for man; being juſt, didſt ſuffer for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt; that thereby, thou mighteſt make us of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, righteous; of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Brethren; of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, Co-heires; of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iles, Kings: Thy Charity was free, unforced, unme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited: Thou lovedſt not
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152049:32"/> ours, but us, not our ſins, but our perſons: Thou didſt informe us by thy Word, reforme us by thy Example, confirme us by thy Miracles, and all this, to expreſſe thy Charity. <hi>O quam ſtupenda Dulcedo, quam invicta Manſuetudo, Regem gloria, pro deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimo vernaculo imò ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miculo crucifigi! What an unſpeakeable Love, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd Charity was it, for the King of glory, to dye for a worme:</hi> and that not for a loving one neither, but for his enemies. Thou <hi>O Ieſus,</hi> didſt lay downe thy Life, thou didſt offer up thy ſelfe, thou gaveſt thy
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152049:32"/> body, and blood for our food, thy Soule, for our Ranſome, thy Deity, a refuge againſt Satan; and all this, to expreſſe thy Charity.</p>
                     <p>Here then is a <hi>Roſe</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paralell, Charity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond compare. There are but three degrees of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: The firſt is, to love them, that love us; this did the Heathen, and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans. The ſecond is, to love them that doe us nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good, nor evill; many there are, that can reach to this degree too. The third is, to love them that hate, and perſecute us. This laſt degree is the chiefeſt, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152049:33"/> may bee expreſſed foure wayes.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, when wee ſpeake well of our Enemies: this is the ſervice of the tongue.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, when we give almes to our enemies: this is the ſervice of our ſtore.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, when wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure paine for our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; this is the ſervice of our body.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, and laſtly, when we dye for our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and this is the ſervice of our life.</p>
                     <p>Many there are who will both ſpeake well, and doe well for their Friends, but who will dye for his Friend? Many will ſpeake
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152049:33"/> well, and doe well for their Friends, but who will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his mouth for his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my? What, not a Tongue for an Enemy? Then I am ſure, no man will willingly offer himſelfe to Death for his Enemy.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Curtius,</hi> and the <hi>Decij</hi> dyed for their Countrey, and fellow-cittizens, but they dyed honourably: <hi>Chriſt</hi> dyed for his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and his perſecutors, and that ignobly. <hi>Hic la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, hoc opus eſt.</hi> This was a worke indeed, atchieved onely by him, who was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the ſonnes of men, even the Sonne of God. But what moved him thus
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152049:34"/> to doe? It was Charity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone that conſtrained him: ſhee was that happy gale of winde, that drove him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Coaſts, ſhe alone was guilty of his Death. <hi>Haec de Coelo Deum depoſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, haec in Cruce poſuit. It was</hi> Charity, <hi>drew him downe from Heaven: It was</hi> Charity, <hi>that faſtened him to the Croſſe.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, unto thee, <hi>O Charity,</hi> to thee, I meane, O God: for God is Love. To thee, I ſay, wee doe ſacrifice our praiſes: For thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the remiſſion of our ſinnes. <hi>God ſo loved the World, that he gave his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten Sonne, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152049:34"/> beleeved in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi> It was thou that didſt give that Vermilian Tincture, to our Celeſtiall <hi>Roſe,</hi> and mad'ſt our <hi>Nazarenus</hi> ſo red in his Paſſion. It was thou that gaveſt him to us, that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt him for us, and in him, haſt given us all things. Thus is <hi>Chriſt</hi> compared to the <hi>Roſe</hi> in Redneſſe, and may juſtly be tearmed <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarenus, The Flower of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The laſt Flower, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> our <hi>Nazarenus</hi> may be compared, is the <hi>Mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gold,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gold.</note> a Flower for this remarkeable: That it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152049:35"/> with the Sunne, and ſhuts with the Sunne: And as the Sunne moves from Eaſt, to Weſt; ſo the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rygold</hi> ſeemes ſtill to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, towards the Sunne, and therefore is called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Ad Solem ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, Ever turning to the Sunne.</hi> Our <hi>Nazarenus</hi> may be called a <hi>Marygold,</hi> in reſpect of his Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: Hee began his life in Obedience to the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall Law, in his Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and ended his life in Obedience to the Morall Law, in his Paſſion. The Sunne, you know, is the eye of the World, and that bright Light, which il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminates
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152049:35"/> all Regions. To ſuch a Light is Gods Law compared: <hi>Thy Word is a Lanthorne to my feete, and a light unto my pathes. Pſal.</hi> 119.105.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.105.</note> Here is the Sun, Gods Law: Behold now the <hi>Marygold, Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> opening with this Sunne. For the firſt words of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which the Scripture particularly ſets downe, that he ſpake, were words of obedience to the Law: <hi>Know yee not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that I muſt be about my Fathers buſineſſe? Luke</hi> 2.49. Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the Sunne: For at his Death, he cryes <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummatum eſt, It is finiſhed. Iohn</hi> 19.30. In his whole
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152049:36"/> life, his face inclined to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Sunne: For hee might truely ſay, in the words of the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, I have alwayes ſet thy Law before my face. Pſalm.</hi> 119. And as the face of the <hi>Cherubine</hi> looked al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, towards the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy-ſeate: ſo the face of this <hi>Marygold,</hi> was alwayes, towards the Sun of Gods Law. He was ſo addicted thereunto, that <hi>it was his meate, to doe the Will of him that ſent him, and to finiſh his Worke. Iohn</hi> 4.34.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 4.34</note> The Lord calls him, <hi>His righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Servant, who ſhall juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie many by his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> Eſay 53.11. <hi>His
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152049:36"/> righteous Servant:</hi> There is the exactneſſe of his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. <hi>Who ſhall juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie many by his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> there's the Superro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of his Merits. Thus is <hi>Chriſt</hi> compared to the <hi>Marygold,</hi> and may bee juſtly tearmed <hi>Nazarenus, The Flower of Obedience.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here then have I let you ſee a Garden of fragrant Flowers, to the ſight beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, to the ſmell odori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous. What remaines, but that we enter into this Garden, and gather of theſe Flowers, from the Croſſe of our Saviour; and making Garlands thereof, weare them upon our
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152049:37"/> Heads, and Poſes, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the boſome of our Hearts: O thou ſweet <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarenus,</hi> draw us by thy odoriferous ſent after thee, yea, unto thee: Lead us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Garden, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us, with the fragrancy of thy Celeſtiall Flowers. Nay, make us, O bleſſed <hi>Nazarenus,</hi> ſpirituall Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens unto thy ſelfe: Set in our Hearts ſome ſlippes of theſe Flowers, purge us from the weeds of vice, and inſteed thereof, make Humility to flouriſh in our cogitations, Innocency, in our converſations, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, in our appetites, Charity, in our affections,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152049:37"/> and Obedience, in all our actions: to the Salvation of our Soules, the good example of our Brethren: To the glory, and praiſe of thee our bleſſed Saviour, who wert, art, and ever ſhalt be, <hi>Ieſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth.</hi> And ſo I come to the laſt word of <hi>Pilates</hi> Inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>King of the Iewes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>[King of the Iewes.]</head>
                     <p>THeſe were the laſt words of <hi>Pilates</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, faſtened upon the Croſſe, whereon our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>Chriſt</hi> was crucified, which is the third preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Cauſe of his Crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152049:38"/> Little thought <hi>Pilate,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was truely <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> when he ſet up this Title: For he received this Name, not by <hi>Pilates</hi> Inſcription onely, but by his Fathers Ordination. For hee is our Great King, who ruleth all things; who hath ſubdued all our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, tryumphing, on his Croſſe, over the World, the Fleſh, and the Devill.</p>
                     <p>He is called <hi>The King of the Iewes,</hi> not carnally, but ſpiritually; not of thoſe that were of the ſeede one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but of ſuch as are of the Faith of <hi>Abraham:</hi> that is, of ſuch as beleeve with the heart, and confeſſe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152049:38"/> with the mouth, that he is their King, and Governor.</p>
                     <p>This Title was not firſt given him upon the Croſſe: for the Prophets did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of it before. <hi>I have ſet my King upon my Holy Hill of Syon,</hi> ſayes <hi>David. Pſal.</hi> 2.6. And ſo the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zachary,</hi> Chap. 9. ver. 9. <hi>Rejoyce greatly, thou Daughter of</hi> Syon, <hi>ſhout out, thou Daughter of</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem: <hi>Behold, thy King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth unto thee. Hee is juſt, and having Salvation, low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, riding upon an Aſſe.</hi> His Dominion and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was fore-told by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> Chap. 7. verſ. 14. <hi>There was given him Dominion,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152049:39"/> and Glory, and a Kingdome, that all people, Nations, and languages ſhould ſerve him: His Dominion is an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Dominion, which ſhall not paſſe away; and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which ſhall not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi> It is he that is <hi>Rex Regum, Dominus Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantium: The King of Kings, and Lord of Lords. Rev.</hi> 19.16.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.16</note> With this Title did the Wiſe men ſeeke him: <hi>Math.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Where is hee that is borne, King of the Iewes?</hi> With this Title did the Souldiers deride him. <hi>Math.</hi> 27.29. <hi>Haile King of the Iewes.</hi> And with this Title, did <hi>Pilate</hi> thinke to diſhonour
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152049:39"/> him, as it is in this Text, <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth, King of the Iewes.</hi> A King indeed hee was, though <hi>Pilate</hi> knew it not; whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, though it be in this World, yet is it not of this World; having nothing in it, that is Temporall, or Terreſtriall, but all Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and Celeſtiall; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending not upon Man; but upon God; conſiſting not in Riches, Pompe, Cities, Caſtles, Forts, Armies; <hi>But in Righteouſneſſe, peace, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt. Rom.</hi> 14.17. He is univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Monarch, in whoſe hands are the hearts of Kings, whoſe Vicegerents
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152049:40"/> onely they are heere upon Earth.</p>
                     <p>The Pope weares a Triple Crowne, in token of his three-fold King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: In Heaven, in Earth, and in Hell, or Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. What he aſſumes uſurpingly, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> enjoyes properly: For hee is a King, <hi>Regens in Coelo per gloriam, in Mundo, per gratiam, in Inferno, per juſtitiam. A King</hi> (I ſay) <hi>reigning in Heaven, by his Glory, in Earth, by his Grace, in Hell, by his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</hi> Unto this Kingdome <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath a Triple right.</p>
                     <p>The firſt, as hee is God, coequall with the Father,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152049:40"/> 
                        <hi>by whom all things were made: John</hi> 1.3.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 1.3.</note> and this he is, <hi>Iure Creationis, By right of Creation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, he is King, as hee is the Sonne of God, whom the Father hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Heire of all things. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. And this is <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Patris, By the donation of his Father: All power is given me both in Heaven, and Earth. Math.</hi> 28.18.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, he is King, as he is Mediator betweene God and Man: And this is <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Redemptionis, By the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Redemption:</hi> and thus <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, he is here ſtyled, <hi>Rex Iudaeorum, King of the Iewes.</hi> As hee is then our
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152049:41"/> 
                        <hi>Ieſus,</hi> ſo is hee our King. The which Title <hi>King,</hi> preſuppoſes a Kingdome: and a Kingdome, preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes Subjects, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects preſuppoſed Lawes, and Government. In the handling therefore, of this Kingly Office, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned, (though but in a word) to unfold unto you a whole Commonwealth: <hi>Chriſts</hi> Office, his Kingdome, his Subjects, and his Government. And firſt of his Office, he is <hi>Rex, A King.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The word <hi>King</hi> imports a Soveraigne power over Subjects, whereof, the Scripture records foure ſorts.</p>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:152049:41"/>
                     <p>Firſt, there is <hi>Rex infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis, An infernall King,</hi> which is the Devill, called by <hi>Iob,</hi> Chap. 41. the laſt Verſe, <hi>Rex ſuper omnes fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os ſuperbiae, A King over all the children of pride.</hi> And alſo tearmed by our Saviour, <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.31. <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps mundi, The Prince of this world.</hi> And by St. <hi>Paul, Eph.</hi> 2.2.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2.</note> 
                        <hi>Princeps Aëris, The Prince of the Ayre.</hi> And by St. <hi>Iohn, Rev.</hi> 9.11. <hi>King of Locuſts, Abaddon</hi> by name, a deſtroyer by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whoſe Kingdome is of this world, whoſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are the ſlaves of ſin, and children of Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: whoſe government
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152049:42"/> is wickedneſſe, and whoſe Law, is the tranſgreſſion of all Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, there is <hi>Rex temporalis, A temporall King;</hi> ſuch as <hi>Saul, David, Solomon, Ezechias,</hi> and others were in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Such as are now Kings of the Nations. This Kingdome is both in this world, and of this world: Their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, men ordered by Reaſon, and governed by Lawes Civill, and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, there is <hi>Rex ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualis, A ſpirituall King;</hi> ſuch is every godly Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: A King, and a Prieſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152049:42"/> to God, ſubſtituted under <hi>Chriſt.</hi> His Subjects are his affections, which hee commands, neither by the Law of Reaſon, nor by the Law of Nature, but by the Law of Grace, which is the Word of God.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, and laſtly there is <hi>Rex aeternalis, An eternall, and an everlaſting King,</hi> and this is he, who is here entitled, <hi>Rex Iudaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, King of the Iewes.</hi> The Regality of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was directly typified by the Crowne, that was about the Arke: <hi>Exod.</hi> 37.2. the which Arke repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented <hi>Chriſt.</hi> His Princely function was ſtrangely
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152049:43"/> prefigured in <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decke,</hi> who was both King, and Prieſt: In <hi>David,</hi> who was both King, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: In <hi>Solomon,</hi> who was a Type of our Saviour, in his Soveraignty, in his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, in his Wiſedome, in his Peace, excelling all the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in wealth, in Iudgement, and in tranquility: hereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling our Saviours Kingly Office, in his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, his Propheticall, in his Wiſedome; his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or Mediatorſhip, in his Peace. This is that King, whom the Angell fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told to <hi>Mary, Luke</hi> 1.33. <hi>Hee ſhall reigne over his
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152049:43"/> houſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>for ever, and of his Kingdome, there ſhall bee no end.</hi> This is that King, of whom the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.6.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal</hi> 8.6.</note> 
                        <hi>Who was crowned with glory, and honour, and to whom, God gave Dominion over the workes of his hands, and put all things under his feete.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Laſtly, This is that King, who is above all Kings; for other Kings Countries are bounded, his without limits; their time of Reigning is deſigned, his endures World without end; their power exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth but unto the body, his both to Soule, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152049:44"/> he derives his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from none, they all from him; and therefore is moſt fit to bee honoured with this Royall Title, <hi>King of the Iewes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There are ſixe things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, to make a good King.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>He muſt be</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 Wiſe, to governe.</item>
                           <item>2 Liberall, to reward.</item>
                           <item>3 Mighty, to defend.</item>
                           <item>4 Indifferent, to judge</item>
                           <item>5 Severe, to puniſh.</item>
                           <item>6 Peaceable, to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heſe ſix properties met <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>n <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which ſhews <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> hee was a good King: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t, he is a wiſe King: <hi>For
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:152049:44"/> it pleaſed his Father, that in him all fulneſſe ſhould dwell.</hi> 1 <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.19.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.19.</note> What fulneſſe? Even the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Wiſedome; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is he called, <hi>The Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Father. Eſay</hi> 11.2. For in him did the God-head dwell <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> inſtructing him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, what he had to doe. The <hi>Jewes</hi> once ſayd of <hi>Chriſt, That hee did all things well:</hi> We may ſay, he ruleth all things wiſely, diverting all to his owne glory, and the good of the Church. He is wiſe, &amp; ſees all things; hee is Prudent, and conſiders all things: he is provident, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152049:45"/> all things which may prejudiſe his Church, which is his Kingdome: therefore hee is called, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> 9.6. <hi>Admirabilis Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilarius, The wonderfull Councellour:</hi> For he is that Wiſedome, which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.12.13. <hi>That dwells with Prudence, that findes out witty inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: Councell is his, and ſound Wiſedome: Hee is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and ſtrength: by him Kings reigne, and Princes decree Iuſtice.</hi> Wherefore, albeit <hi>Chriſt,</hi> our King, ſuffer Schiſmes in his Church, Diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his Kingdome, and the Enemy to prevaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152049:45"/> his Subjects; yet this is not for want of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to governe, but that thereby Antichriſt may be revealed, the Loyalty of his owne Subjects proved, and tryed, and his enemies confounded with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confuſion. Therefore, whatſoever <hi>Turkes, Iewes,</hi> or <hi>Heathen</hi> judge of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> we muſt confeſſe that he is <hi>Rex ſapiens,</hi> A wiſe King.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall King: Heathen Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories have recorded the Munificence of <hi>Alexander,</hi> the Liberality of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the Bounty of <hi>Titus Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian,</hi> of <hi>Ptolomeus</hi> the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane,</hi> and of <hi>Pertinax</hi> the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:152049:46"/> Emperour. And ſacred Scriptures acquaint us with the like, in <hi>David, Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Ahaſuerus,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, famous for their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality. But what is their bounty, if compared with the Liberality of our <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, King of the Iewes?</hi> He exceeds all others herein, as the Sunne doth other Starres in Brightneſſe. <hi>When hee aſcended up on high, he led captivity cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and gave gifts unto men, Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. behold his Bounty: <hi>Behold, I come quickly,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and my reward is with me, to give to every one according to his workes. Rev.</hi> 22.12. A Cup
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152049:46"/> of cold water ſhall not bee unrewarded, if it bee given to a Diſciple, in the Name of a Diſciple. <hi>Chriſts</hi> boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty farre exceeds all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glories, be they never ſo great, be they never ſo many. <hi>Ptolomee</hi> the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane</hi> Captaine, had ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed himſelfe unto li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality, that, when a poore ſouldier craved his Almes, he having at that time in preſent nothing to beſtow upon him, gave him his ſhooes off his feet, ſaying, <hi>My friend, make thy profit of theſe; for I had rather goe bare-foote, than thou ſhouldſt ſuffer ſo much.</hi> But what hath <hi>Chriſt</hi> given
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152049:47"/> to us? Not his ſhooes, but the garments of his owne Righteouſneſſe, to cover us, his fleſh, to feed us; his Blood, to refreſh us, his Life, to revive us: He hath made us his friends, yea, Co-heires with himſelfe; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. He hath made us his ſheepe: <hi>He is the good ſhepheard, that laid down his life for his ſheepe. Iohn</hi> 10.11. Hee hath made us his Branches: <hi>I am the Vine, and yee are the branches,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.5. He hath made us his Members: <hi>For hee is the Head, and the whole Church is Body.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27. Nay, <hi>Chriſt</hi> being King, to expreſſe his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152049:47"/> gives petty Crownes, or Coronets to all his Saints: Therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. <hi>He hath made us Kings, and Prieſts to God.</hi> If Kings, where are our Crownes? Why, the whole Church hath a Crowne, figured by the Crowne of <hi>Ieruſalem. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zech.</hi> 16.12. <hi>I put a Jewell on thy forehead, and Eare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings in thine eares, and a beautifull Crowne upon thy Head.</hi> Nay, more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, every member of <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath a Crowne. <hi>There is a Crowne for a faithfull Husband: A ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Woman is a Crowne to her Husband,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152049:48"/> Prov.</hi> 12.4. There is a Crowne for the wiſe. <hi>The fooliſh inherit folly, but the prudent are crowned with knowledge. Prov.</hi> 14.18. There is a Crowne for Children, and another for Parents. <hi>Childrens Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are the Crowne of the aged,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Prov. 17.6</note> 
                        <hi>and the glory of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, are their Fathers.</hi> There is a Crowne for the faithfull Paſtor; thus Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Gaudium, &amp; Corona, His Ioy, and his Crowne. Phil.</hi> 4.1.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.1.</note> And the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> the like: 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.19. where they are tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Apoſtle, <hi>The Hope, the Joy, or the Crowne
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152049:48"/> of his rejoycing.</hi> Theſe are Crownes given here: but what Crownes may they expect hereafter? <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath one Crowne, but diſtinguiſhed in Scripture, by three denominations: the which Crowne he will beſtow upon his <hi>Saints,</hi> and all thoſe that feare him: The Crowne of Life, the Crowne of Glory, and the Crowne of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The firſt is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.12.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.12</note> 
                        <hi>Bleſsed is the man, who endureth temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; for when he is tryed, hee ſhall receive the crowne of Life, the which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love him,</hi> This was likewiſe
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:152049:49"/> promiſed by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the Angell of the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> Rev, 2.10.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
                        <hi>Be thou faithfull unto Death, and I will give thee the Crowne of Life.</hi> The ſecond is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to <hi>Chriſts</hi> faithfull Miniſters: For <hi>St. Peter</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courages them, ſaying, <hi>When the chiefe Shepheard ſhall appeare, yee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Crowne of Glory, which fadeth not away.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4. Of the third, <hi>St. Paul</hi> aſſures himſelfe, <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith, hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth is layd up for mee a Crowne of Righteouſneſſe.</hi> Thus, as there is none
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:152049:49"/> crowned, except they ſtrive: ſo there are none that ſtrive aright, and fight lawfully in <hi>Chriſts</hi> warefare, but ſhal be crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; none ſhall be his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but ſhall bee rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; <hi>Iob</hi> ſhall not ſerve God for naught: but if hee ſerve him, he ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed. Wherefore we cannot, but truely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that he, who is <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> is <hi>Rex liberalis,</hi> A bountifull King.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not onely a wiſe, and a liberall, but alſo a powerfull, and a mighty King, whoſe power is ſeene in two things eſpecially, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152049:50"/> his enemies, and in defending his Subjects. The confuſion of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, is an eſſentiall part of his government: for he could never have beene a ſufficient Saviour, if he had not, and did not confound the enemies of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. But that he ſhould ſo doe, was propheſied by <hi>David, Pſal</hi> 2.9. <hi>Thou ſhalt bruiſe them with a rod of Iron, and breake them in pieces like a Potters veſſell.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.9. which was purpoſely penned for <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> but typically deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth <hi>Chriſt:</hi> He ſaith, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>He ſhall breake in pieces the oppreſſor:</hi> and <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152049:50"/> 
                        <hi>And his enemies ſhall lick the duſt:</hi> whereby the Prophet would inſinuate <hi>Chriſts</hi> power, in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and in the confuſion of his foes: What greater Enemy than the Devill? yet, <hi>the God of peace ſhall ſhortly tread Satan under our feet,</hi> ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. How ſtrong an enemy is the World to Chriſts Kingdome? yet <hi>be of good cheere, I have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome the World,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi> to his Diſciples, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. <hi>ver.</hi> the laſt. How po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent an enemy is Sinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Chriſts</hi> Kingdome? yet <hi>Chriſt came in the fleſh,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:152049:51"/> that he might condemne ſin in the fleſh,</hi> ſayes the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. And ſo likewiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Our old man, which is ſinne, is cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with Chriſt, that the body of ſinne might bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; and therefore ſinne hath no more dominion over us.</hi> What is become of that Adverſary, which cut off all <hi>Christs</hi> Subjects, namely, Death? St. <hi>Paul</hi> tels us plainely, <hi>That Death is ſwallowed up in victory:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54.</note> And <hi>Chriſt</hi> rides tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly, ſaying, <hi>O Death, where is thy ſting? O Grave, where is thy victory?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55.</p>
                     <p>How hath <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi>
                        <pb n="125" facs="tcp:152049:51"/> brought to confuſion the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and their Adherents, which would not have him reigne over them? Behold the power of this <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> in the ſubverſion of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the deſtruction of <hi>Herod,</hi> the confuſion of <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate, the ruine of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Hereticks, and their Hereſies, which were the Divels ſouldiers, and foes unto Chriſts Kingdome: Onely, there remaines the fall of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let-coloured Whore, and the deſtruction of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, that ſonne of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whom our <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſhall deſtroy with the breath of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:152049:52"/> his mouth: ſo let all thine enemies periſh O Lord.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, Chriſts power is manifeſted in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of his Subjects: He is not onely <hi>Rex titularis,</hi> but alſo <hi>Rex tutelaris; Not onely a Titular, but alſo a Tutelar King.</hi> And as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua,</hi> not onely deſtroyed the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected <hi>Iſrael</hi> all his dayes: So Chriſt, (a Type of whom <hi>Ioſua</hi> was) doth not onely confound his foes, but alſo confirme his friends; deſtroying his enemies, but protecting his Subjects: For he is our Judge, he is our Law-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, he is our King, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:152049:52"/> he will ſave us. It is hee that hath ſaved the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the needy, it is he that hath, and will for ever deliver the poore, that hath no helper: It is hee, that hath promiſed to bee with his Church, unto the end of the World: As to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect it by his Spirit, ſo to protect it by his power. It is hee that keepeth <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and neither ſlumbreth, nor ſleepeth. Hayle then, O hayle thou victorious King both of Heaven, and Earth, that haſt overcome the <hi>fleſh</hi> within mee, the <hi>world</hi> without me, <hi>Death</hi> for me, and the <hi>Devill</hi> againſt me: That doeſt correct me
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:152049:53"/> in thy mercy, direct me in thy truth, and protect me by thy power, from all my Adverſaries: Thou art the Lord, the Lord ſtrong, and mighty, thy Name is a ſtrong Tower, to which I flye, and am ſecure: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will confeſſe thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and acknowledge, that <hi>the King of the Iewes,</hi> is <hi>Rex potens, A powerfull King.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fourthly, a good King muſt be an indifferent, an impartiall King; to judge the cauſe of the poore, as well as of the rich; of the weake, as well as of the mighty; reſpecting not the Condition of the perſon,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:152049:53"/> but the Equity of the cauſe; not countenancing the rich man, for his Wealth, nor contemning the poore man, for his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty: for it is an honour to a Prince, to bee a poore mans King.</p>
                     <p>Such a one is our <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> who is not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall in his temporall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, nor will be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall in his eternall Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Therefore is hee ſtyled by Saint <hi>Paul, The juſt Iudge, that ſhall render unto every one according to his workes.</hi> 2. Tim. 4.8. <hi>For of a truth, God is no reſpecter of perſons,</hi> ſayes the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle St. <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 10.34.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152049:54"/> For where ſin is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, there is puniſhment inflicted, bee it King, or Beggar; rich, or poore; <hi>Iew,</hi> or <hi>Gentile:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the World may truely ſay, that our <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> is <hi>Rex juſtus, A righteous King.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Againe, fiftly, a good King muſt bee ſevere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as are incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible, and will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend. It is obſerved by <hi>Cicero, That it is the ruine of a Common-wealth, when Iudgement given, is revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and the execution of the Law ſtopped againſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors.</hi> And the ſaying of <hi>Solomon</hi> is, <hi>Becauſe Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152049:54"/> againſt evill doers is not executed ſpeedily, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the hearts of the ſonnes of men are fully ſet to doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill. Eccleſ.</hi> 8.11.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.11.</note> But <hi>Chriſt,</hi> like a ſevere King, will at the length judge, and puniſh the wicked. If <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> will not bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together under his wings, ſhe ſhall be at the laſt left deſolate. <hi>Luke</hi> 13. <hi>verſ.</hi> the laſt: And if the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> wil not <hi>remember from whence ſhe is falne, and repent, and doe her firſt workes, hee will come againſt her ſhortly, and remove away her Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke. Rev.</hi> 2.5. And at the laſt day, what a juſt Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:152049:55"/> ſhall hee pronounce, both to the godly, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wicked, ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Sheepe on the right hand, and the Goats on the left; when he ſhall ſay unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> one, <hi>Come yee bleſſed of the Father receive the Kingdome prepared for you, from the beginning of the world:</hi> but unto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Goe yee curſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devill, and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> Thus is <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> an impartiall King, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing all the wicked within his Dominions, and rewarding the good: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may ſay, that our <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> is <hi>Rex ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verus,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152049:55"/> A ſevere King.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſixt, and laſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of a good King, is, that hee be <hi>Pacificus, A peace-maker,</hi> and that, both in his owne Kingdome, and abroad: This is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, that <hi>Plutarch</hi> gives to <hi>Numa Pompilius,</hi> in whoſe daies, the Temple of <hi>Ianus</hi> was kept ſhut, for the ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ce of Forty yeares. And this praiſe in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> is given to <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> that during his Reigne, <hi>Iſrael</hi> was neither moleſted with civill Wars at home, nor forraigne, with other Nations; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in being a Type of our <hi>King of the Jewes,</hi> who was
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152049:56"/> called, long before he was borne, <hi>Princeps pacis, The Prince of peace. Eſay</hi> 9.6. He was borne in a time of a generall peace, when he wrought our peace on Earth; he is our Peace: <hi>He came, and preached peace unto them, that were a farre off, and to them that were nigh. Eph.</hi> 2.17 Juſtly did <hi>Chriſt</hi> merit to bee called <hi>The Prince of peace;</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his comming, there were many Queſtions in the World, which at his comming, hee fully deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</p>
                     <p>The firſt queſtion was in the ſacred Trinity, and that was this:</p>
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:152049:56"/>
                     <p> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Whether Man, having tranſgreſſed, ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, ſeeing the Angels, that fell, were not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed? And it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined Affirmatively, that Man ſhould be redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, though the Angels were not: Becauſe the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſinned by no ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: whereas Man ſinned by the ſuggeſtion, and fraud of Satan. Secondly, becauſe the Angels were ſpirits, and ſhould have ſtood firmely in Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: whereas Man did conſiſt of fleſh, and blood, which is alwayes prone to fall; according to that of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152049:57"/> our Saviour, <hi>Math.</hi> 26.41. <hi>The Spirit indeed is willing, but the Fleſh is weake.</hi> Thirdly, becauſe the whole Nature of Angels fell not, but onely ſome, that were Rebellious: whereas the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Mankinde fell, as having ſinned in the roote; and pitty it was, that ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Creature ſhould wholly periſh. Fourthly, becauſe the fall of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, was the ruine of an Angell, and made him paſt recovery: Whereas the fall of man, made him not paſt recoverie.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond Queſtion in the Holy Trinity was, who
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:152049:57"/> ſhould worke this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption? whether the Father, or the Sonne, or to Holy Ghoſt? And it was determined, that the Sonne ſhould doe it: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe unto the Father is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed Power, unto the Sonne, Wiſedome; unto the Holy Ghoſt, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Now <hi>Lucifer</hi> ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly deſired Gods Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and therefore ſinned againſt the Father: Man deſired Gods Wiſedome, <hi>Yee ſhall be as Gods, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, and evill:</hi> and therefore, ſinned againſt the Sonne: Antichriſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpes the Goodneſſe of the Holy Ghoſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152049:58"/> ſinnes againſt the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, and is the ſonne of perdition, and cannot be ſaved. Now <hi>Ejus eſt liberare, &amp;c.</hi> It behooveth him, that receiveth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, to give the Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; and Man, that had offended againſt the Son, muſt be redeemed by the Sonne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third Queſtion in the ſacred Trinity, was, How Man ſhould be redeemed? whether by power, or condigne ſatisfaction? And it was determined, not by power, but by puniſhment: And ſeeing man had offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by Pride, Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and carnall delight,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:152049:58"/> 
                        <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Sonne of God, made ſatisfaction, by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Obedience, and the ſuffering of Death.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth Queſtion was, betweene God, and Man: for God complained againſt Man, that hee had offended him: and Man complained againſt God, that God had forſaken him: <hi>Chriſt</hi> tooke away this difference, by becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a Mediator.</p>
                     <p>Now, a Mediator muſt have three properties: Community, Authority, and Power: Community, hee muſt be indifferent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene both; ſo was <hi>Chriſt,</hi> having Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:152049:59"/> with God, as God; and Community Authority with Man, as Man. Hee muſt have Authority too, to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue the Cauſe on either ſide: So had <hi>Chriſt,</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for his Father, that Man had broken his Law: pleading for Man, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſatisfaction. He muſt alſo have Power, upon the determination of the cauſe, to make a Reconciliation; ſo had <hi>Chriſt, having made peace, through the blood of that his Croſſe, to reconcile all things to himſelfe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be things in Earth, or things in Heaven.</hi> Coloſ. 1.20.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fift Queſtion was,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:152049:59"/> betweene Man, and Satan: The Devill pleaded right unto Mankinde, who had ſold himſelfe to him, for an Apple: The difference is taken away by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who pleads, the Apple to bee none of the Devils, and therefore, hee bought him not with his owne: but <hi>Chriſt</hi> redeemed him, <hi>not with Silver, or Gold, but with his owne precious blood.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18.19. And mans ſinne could not ſo much exceede in Demerit, as <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſufferings did in Merit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The ſixt, and the laſt Queſtion, was betweene Man, and Woman: For
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152049:60"/> Man complained of the Woman, that ſhe had allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him; and the Woman of the Man, that he ſhould have reprooved her; but becauſe they were both Authors of their owne perdition, <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath made them both partakers of his Redemption. Hee tooke fleſh of a Woman, that Women might not thinke themſelves excluded: but in the perſon of a Man, that Man thereby might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed: Thus hath Chriſt, in the world, wrought a world of Peace for us, not peace with the world: For, <hi>Non veni mittere pacem,</hi> (ſaith he) but peace with
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:152049:60"/> God, peace with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, peace with Men, peace with the Creatures, and peace with our owne Conſciences. Wherefore we may juſtly ſay, that our <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> is <hi>Rex pacificus, A peaceable King.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And thus we have ſeene the Condition of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> how he hath approved himſelfe a good King: For he is wiſe, liberall, powerfull, indifferent, ſevere, and peaceable; anſwerable to which qualities, are all his Actions. For every worke of his, is either a worke of VViſedome, or a worke
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:152049:61"/> of Mercy; or a worke of power, or a worke of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; or a worke of Juſtice, or a worke of Peace; as if he intended in all things, to ſhew himſelfe a <hi>King</hi> for our commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: But as the King of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> changed his habit, and diſguiſed himſelfe, when he went into the Battell at <hi>Ramoth-Gilead,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.30.<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.30.</note> ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> indeed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed himſelfe, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the forme of God, and equall with God, took upon him the ſhape of a Servant, continuing ever, though unknowne to the wicked <hi>Iewes, [Ieſus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth, King of the Iewes.]</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:152049:85"/>
                     <p>Wherefore, ſeeing wee have but one Soveraigne Monarch, who is God, and Man, and <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> that hath the ſole power to command our ſoules, let us never deny our Allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to him: Let us ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make any confederacy, or enthrall our ſelves to the World, the Fleſh, or the Divell, which would ſoone get the Dominion over us, and make us their vaſſals. And although all worldlings, drunkards, and uncleane perſons, and all that continue in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, without repentance, have made themſelves bond-ſlaues unto theſe Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:152049:86"/> yet let us, whom God hath called to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of his Saints in loue, ſtand faſt in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, wherewith <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath made us free: not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering our ſoules to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled againe, with the yoake of bondage. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. Their ſervice is nothing but miſery, and wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: For <hi>Mundus deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, Caro inficit, Diabolus deſtruit: The World will deceive us, the Fleſh will infect us, and the Devill will deſtroy us:</hi> from ſuch Kings, Good Lord deliver us. Onely, O bleſſed <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> bee thou our ſpirituall Soveraigne; thou
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:152049:86"/> art wiſe, and wilt inſtruct us; thou art liberall, and wilt reward us; thou art mighty, and wilt defend us; thou art juſt, and wilt not forget us, thou art ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, and wilt not ſuffer the wicked to tryumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us; thou art peaceable, yea, our peace, for thou haſt wrought Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation with God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; who with thee bee glorified for ever-more. Fly then thou ſinner, from bondage, to liberty; from death, to life; from miſery, to glory: Behold, <hi>The King of the Iewes</hi> calls thee, <hi>Come unto me all yee that are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and heavy laden, and I
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:152049:87"/> will refreſh you. Math.</hi> 11.28. Here is a Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of pardon for thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt, if thou wilt ſeeke it, if thou wilt embrace it. He that is <hi>King of the Jewes,</hi> waites when thou wilt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his Subject: <hi>Behold,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>I ſtand at the doore, and knocke, if any man open unto me, I will come in, and ſuppe with him, and he with me. Rev.</hi> 3.20. Set open the gate of thy heart, <hi>and the King of glory will come in Pſal.</hi> 24.7. He will come <hi>tibi, ſi credis, contra te, ſi non credis: If thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him with faith, and repentance, hee will come to comfort thee; if neither
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:152049:87"/> with faith, nor repentance, hee will come to confound thee.</hi> If thou become a Subject, hee will defend thee; if thou continue an enemy, hee will deſtroy thee.</p>
                     <p>Now is <hi>Chriſt</hi> comming into thy Soule, as once hee came to <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> Oh, beleeve that he is thy <hi>King,</hi> entertaine him joyfully; cut downe the Branches of old <hi>Adams</hi> corruption, put off the ragges of ſinne, ſpread them in the way, and let thy Saviour tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on them: Receive him with hearty acclamations, and ſay, <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to the Sonne of <hi>David, Bleſsed
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:152049:88"/> is hee that commeth in the Name of the Lord,</hi> Hoſanna <hi>in the higheſt.</hi> Thus much touching the Office of our <hi>Jeſus, He is a King.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, for that a King does neceſſarily preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Kingdome, for they are Relatives; the next thing wee are to treate of, is his Kingdome.</p>
                     <p>There was never any earthly Empire, but had his limits, and was boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with ſome parts of the habitable World: The <hi>Aſſyrian, Grecian, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, though they ſpread themſelves farre, and wide, yet was there alwayes
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:152049:88"/> ſome Lands, Nations, and Kingdomes exempt from their Dominion: There was never any earthly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, that was perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but, as it had a time of increaſe, ſo hath it a time of decreaſe; being, either by ſedition, or forraigne invaſion, or ſome vice, or other, brought to ruine: herein reſembling the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body of man, which hath a time to bee concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, a time to bee nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and a time to bee brought unto perfection: But when it hath attained his <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>His full growth,</hi> it declines againe, as the Sunne, when hee is come
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:152049:89"/> to the Meridian; and in tract of time, either by its owne imbecility, or (it may be) ſooner, by diſeaſes, or ſooneſt of all, by ſudden Death, droppes into the Grave.</p>
                     <p>As it is with this Little world Man, ſo is it with that Great Man, the world; ſubject it is to change, and alteration. Now herein, <hi>Chriſts</hi> Kingdome exceeds all Kingdomes, which, as it is boundleſſe for place, ſo is it endleſſe, for time; infinite in extent, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall for continuance. Hee ſhall reigne over the Houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> for ever, there is his perpetuity; and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:152049:89"/> of his Kingdome there ſhall bee no end, there is his infiniteneſſe.</p>
                     <p>The Kingdome of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is twofold, <hi>Superius,</hi> and <hi>Inferius: His Kingdome which is above, and his Kingdome which is below:</hi> Or rather they are one Kingdome, differenced by two degrees: though uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally we call one, <hi>The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Grace,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>The Kingdome of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> The Kingdome of Grace is that, which our Saviour ſayes, is within us: <hi>Regnum Dei intra vos eſt, The Kingdome of God is within you: Luke</hi> 17.21.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luke</hi> 17.21.</note> wherein CHRIST ſolely
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:152049:90"/> reignes, without ſubſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any Viceroyes, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>s: For the greateſt Monarch, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> the moſt righteous Chriſtian in the World, is in this caſe, but a fellow ſubject, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath no rule over the Soule, or command over the Conſcience, in matters divine, tending to Gods worſhip; though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, in matters Civill, and Pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>icall. For as I have diſtinguiſhed <hi>Chriſt</hi> from a temporall King: ſo may his Kingdome bee diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from the other; the one being wholly ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, the other <hi>Per ſe, &amp; directè,</hi> wholly tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:152049:90"/> This Kingdome or Grace is nothing elſe, but our ſpiritual incorporation into the myſticall body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> being made live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly branches of him, who is the true Vine, being eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed through faith, in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> This Kingdome conſiſts not in worldly dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, terreſtriall Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, Citties, Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, Councellours, <hi>but in Righteouſneſſe, peace, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt. Rom.</hi> 14.17.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17.</note> All are not Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this Kingdome, that are viſibly in this Kingdome: For ſome there are, that are dead Members, rotten Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:152049:91"/> having a ſhew of godlineſſe, but denying the power thereof. Some, againe, there are, which bee but Forraigners, and Aliens, though ſuffered to trade, and traffique in it; yet many of theſe have gotten the outward habite, and have learned the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of this Kingdome, and doe ſo cunningly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, that they cannot bee diſcerned from true ſubjects by any, but by the King himſelfe. This King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is but an initiation of the other: Here have wee the firſt fruits, there wee ſhall have the whole lampe; this is but an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:152049:91"/> penny, that other, the full payment; in this, wee labour, in that, we receive the reward: This is <hi>Chriſts</hi> Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eyard, that, his place of payment; this is his Worke-houſe, that, his Treaſury; this is the Field of War-fare, that, the place of Tryumph: yet here we muſt reigne over our ſelves, before we can be crowned there: For <hi>Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Coelorum ſperare non poteſt, qui propria membra regere non poteſt: Hee can never hope to reigne in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, who doth not firſt reigne over his owne mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers here on Earth.</hi> This Kingdome is not ſo ſecure,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:152049:92"/> as the other; heere many fall away, others are cut off; ſome intrude without their Wedding-garments, and are therefore impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as Spyes. This King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is often diſturbed by ſedition of Hereſies, and Schiſme; oft ſhaken by the guſts of perſecution, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſhrewdly undermyned by privy temptations, but never overwhelmed. For he, who is King thereof, is the Rocke, whereon this Kingdome is immoveably founded: Unto this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome all ſtrangers are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited, the gates or Ports are ſhut to none: For <hi>Gremium Eccleſiae nulli clauditur.</hi>
                        <pb n="159" facs="tcp:152049:92"/> But ſome are unwilling, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vilifie it: the world is a clog to ſome, Pride is a <hi>Remora</hi> to others: Some diſdaine the King, others martyre his meſſengers; not one, of a Thouſand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a true Subject. This Kingdome is the Church militant, which is nothing elſe, but <hi>Numerus credenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, The number of true beleevers;</hi> which is <hi>Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus exigu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s, A ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;</hi> like <hi>Ieremye</hi> Berries, here, and there one, very thinnely ſtrewen, and ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly ſowne: Yet, though they be but few, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence is ſtrong for <hi>Feare not little flocke, it is your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:152049:93"/> pleaſure, to give you a Kingdome. Luke.</hi> 12.32. And ſo I paſſe in my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, (the which God grant wee may all doe in practice,) from the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Grace, unto the Kingdome of Glory; Into which Kingdome, no falſe hearted Subjects are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: <hi>Nullus egreditur emicus, nullus ingreditur inimicus: Out of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>l no friend paſſe, into it ſhall no enemy enter.</hi> There ſhal be no Schiſmes, nor ſeditions; but the God of Peace, ſhall rule all their hearts peaceably: There, <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſhall Reigne over all his Saints as King, and
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:152049:93"/> yet ſhall make them his Friends, nay, his Brethren: <hi>O qualis ille Rex, qui om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſervos ſuos facit amicos, &amp;, quod multo magis eſt, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres. Oh what a bleſſed King is he, who makes all his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, his friends; nay, which is more, his brethren!</hi> There ſhall be peace with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out warre, joy, without heavineſſe; holineſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out impurity; and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, without intermiſſion. This world is our way, that is our Countrey; this our War-fare, that our Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph; this our ſuffering, that our glory: Heere, are we (as it were) in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, there, wee ſhall
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:152049:94"/> poſſeſſe the heavenly <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> the <hi>Metrapolis</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is the <hi>New Ieruſalem,</hi> whoſe glory is unexpreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: If a man had the tongue of men, and Angels, and ſhould undertake a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of it, he that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes it, may very well ſay of it, as the Queene of <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi> did of <hi>Solomons</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that the one halfe of it was not revealed. In it, is no Creature baſe, or thing contemptible, but all things are ſuperabun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly glorious: A glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King, whoſe bleſſed viſion will make us all hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and in whom, we ſhall enjoy all beatitude; glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:152049:94"/> Subjects, even the bleſſed Saints and Angels; a glorious place, farre tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending any earthly Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, or terreſtriall place of pleaſure: Were it poſſible to finde on earth a Citty ſo glorious, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.10. yet were it not to bee compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the glory of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Heavenly Kingdome: There are Riches which cannot rot, pleaſures which cannot fade; Honour, that cannot be loſt; Life, that cannot be expired. <hi>O bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed King of the Iewes,</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py is that man, whom thou chooſeſt, and cauſeſt to approach unto thee, that
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:152049:95"/> hee may dwell in thy Courts; he ſhall be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the goodneſſe of thy Houſe, even of thy holy Temple: It is the King that muſt chooſe him, hee cannot deſerve the dignity of a Subject; for there is <hi>Gratia ſine me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito, Charitas ſine modo: Favour without merit, and Love without meaſure:</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Kingdome can no Enemy reſiſt, upon this Kingdome can no Enemy make invaſion: For this Kingdome was no price gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but the precious blood of the <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> the which blood hee ſhed, to purchaſe this Kingdome
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:152049:95"/> not for himſelfe, but for his Subjects: And ſo I paſſe from this Kingdome, unto the Subjects of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>Rex Iudaeorum, King of the Iewes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>King of the Iewes?</hi> what <hi>Iewes</hi> is hee King of? of thoſe blaſphemous, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious <hi>Iewes,</hi> which cryed out, <hi>Crucifie him, Crucifie him? They were of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue of Satan,</hi> Rev. 3.9.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.9.</note> 
                        <hi>and ſaid they were Iewes, but were not: For all are not of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>that are</hi> Iſrael: <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.6. And ſome, that are not of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> are the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> of God: <hi>For more are the children of the deſolate, than of the married wife. Eſay</hi> 54.1.</p>
                     <pb n="166" facs="tcp:152049:96"/>
                     <p>His Subjects then, are not onely the <hi>Iewes</hi> Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, but the <hi>Iewes</hi> Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, called by the Apoſtle, <hi>The Iſrael of God. Gal.</hi> 6.16 And theſe are ſuch, as are <hi>Nathanaels, true Iſraelites, in whom there is no guile: Iohn</hi> 1.47.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.47.</note> being rather Heires of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, than of his fleſh.</p>
                     <p>It is not then the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that makes a man an <hi>Iſraelite:</hi> and he is not a <hi>Iew,</hi> that is a <hi>Iew</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly; but hee is a <hi>Jew,</hi> that is a <hi>Iew</hi> inwardly, namely, by beleeving in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and doing his Will. As the Kingdome of <hi>Chriſt</hi>
                        <pb n="167" facs="tcp:152049:96"/> is <hi>Diverſè ſecundum, hic, &amp; illic:</hi> ſo are his Subjects divers, either ſuch as are here in the Church mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, whom I may call, his Souldiers; or ſuch as are in the Church Tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, whom I may call his Conquerors.</p>
                     <p>In the Kingdome of Grace, which is the Church Militant, they onely are true Subjects, who, beſides the outward calling of the Goſpell, are made partakers of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward calling of the Spirit; which is the Donation of ſaving Faith, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of heavenly Grace, whereby the heart
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:152049:97"/> is opened, as the heart of <hi>Lydia</hi> was, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14. when ſhee attended unto the things which were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of St. <hi>Paul:</hi> and when a man is made a lively member of <hi>Chriſts</hi> myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body, being both in profeſſion, and practice truely <hi>Chriſts.</hi> And in this Kingdome, though Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects have divers functions, ſome governing as Rulers, both to defend, extend, and enlarge <hi>Chriſts</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: others being go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned, as Inferiors; yet they all jumpe in this, that they are fellow-ſouldiers, labouring in this war-fare: Neither Regality, nor dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:152049:97"/> neither Riches, nor Poverty, exempting them from this ſpirituall functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ghoſtly ſubjection unto <hi>Chriſt</hi> their King.</p>
                     <p>From this Kingdome are excluded, firſt, all ſuch as are without the Pale of the Church, unto whom the Goſpell of <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath not beene preached, as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Pagans, or with whom the Name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is vilified, as <hi>Iewes,</hi> and <hi>Turkes.</hi> Secondly, they are excluded, who are <hi>Iewes</hi> outwardly, but not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly; that is, <hi>Chriſtians</hi> by name, but not by prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice. Hence then are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded all Hereticks, and
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:152049:98"/> Schiſmaticks, being pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke diſturbers of the peace of <hi>Syon:</hi> and all car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Goſpellers, and looſe Libertines, which, by their wickedneſſe, wound the bowels of the Church: and all ſuperficiall Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and diſſembling Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, which privily yeeld themſelves ſervants to ſinne, and ſlaves to the Devill: Theſe are in this Kingdome, but not of this Kingdome; profeſſing <hi>Chriſt</hi> their Soveraigne, but vouchſafing him onely a Reed for his Scepter; wearing his colours, but forſwearing his ſervice; talking of his name, but
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:152049:98"/> not walking in his wayes: Not every one therefore, that receives his Badge of Baptiſme, or maketh an outward ſhow of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, is truely his Subject: For this is but to enter into the utter Court of the Temple; and of theſe may be affirmed that of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Math.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti vocati, pauci electi: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are called, but few are choſen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the Kingdome of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, they onely are Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath redeemed from the earth; for whom hee ſhed his blood, and bare this Title over his Head: As <hi>Chriſt</hi>
                        <pb n="172" facs="tcp:152049:99"/> is King of Heaven <hi>Iure Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ationis, By right of Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> ſo the Angels are his Subjects: But as hee is <hi>Rex Iudaeorum, Iure Redemptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, King of the Jewes by right of Redemption:</hi> So, none are his Subjects, but ſuch as are ſaved by him. For this was the end, why he became <hi>The King of the Iewes, That wee ſhould bee ſaved from our enemies, and from the hands of all that hate us. Luke</hi> 2.71.</p>
                     <p>For as St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">St. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                        </note> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <hi>Non Rex</hi> Iſrael <hi>Chriſtus, ad exigendum tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butum, vel exercitum ferro armatum, hoſteſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> viſibiliter debellandum: ſed Rex</hi> Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:152049:99"/> 
                        <hi>quod mentes regat, quod in aeternum conſulat, quod in Regnum Coelorum credentes, ſperantes, amantes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducat: Chriſt was not the King of the Iewes, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Tribute, or to raiſe an Army, or viſibly to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh enemies: but hee was the King of the Iewes, to rule mens hearts and mindes, to counſell them eternally, and to bring all thoſe, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in him, hope in him, and truely love him, unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting life.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Happy then is that man, who is a Subject in the Kingdome of Grace: but thrice happy is he, who is a Subject in the Kingdome
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:152049:100"/> of Glory: For he ſhall be glorious in his body: <hi>This corruptible muſt put on in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption:</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.53.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.53.</note> but much more glorious in his ſoule: for <hi>Qualis tunc erit ſplendor animarum, quando lux corporis, Solis habebit claritatem?</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auguſt. How great ſhall the ſplendor of their ſoules be, when their bodies ſhall ſhine as the Sunne in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament?</hi> Their felicity ſhall be ſuch, as that they ſhall deſire to dwell there for ever, as <hi>Peter</hi> did on Mount <hi>Thabor:</hi> And good Reaſon, ſeeing they ſhall be poſſeſſed of ſuch hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, as neither eye hath
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:152049:100"/> ſeene, nor eare hath heard, nor hath it entred into the heart of man to conceiue. The which happineſſe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wee cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, Grant, ô Lord, that we may be comprehended of it; and ſo I paſſe from the Subjects, unto the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which is the laſt thing conſiderable in the Text.</p>
                     <p>This Mighty Monarch, this <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernes not his ſubjects by humane Lawes, and civill policies; but by his owne Law, called by St. <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 6.2.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2.</note> 
                        <hi>The Law of Chriſt:</hi> Now this Law is nothing
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:152049:101"/> elſe, but the Word of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by which Word wee ſhall be judged at the latter day, ſayes our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our:</hi> His Word muſt rule us outwardly, and his <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> inwardly; the one as a Law, the other as a Guide. We offend not, if we tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe not his Word; we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey not, if we erre from it. This Law of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he governes, is like the Lawes of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> unalterable: It ſhall bee an everlaſting Law, eſpecially that new Commandement which he gave us, namely, <hi>That we ſhould love one another.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, as this Kingdome,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:152049:101"/> and the government there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is ſpirituall, and ſtands not in the glittering ſhew of this world, nor in any thing deſireable by fleſh, and blood, as the two ſonnes of <hi>Zebedee</hi> vainely imagined; but ruleth in the heart, and reines: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lawes of this Kingdome, and the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment thereof, requires the inward righteouſneſſe of the heart, binding not onely the outward act, but the Conſcience: For the Authority, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the King, is that, whereby he, by his Word, and by his Spirit, (for the Word barely, without the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:152049:102"/> Spirit, pierces not into the heart:) effecteth, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the converſion of thoſe that are to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and glorifies him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the everſion, and confuſion of the reſt. For as the Kingdome of the Goſpell, is the meanes to bring us to the Kingdome of Grace: ſo the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Grace, doth bring us to the Kingdome of Glory: And none ſhall enter into the Kingdome of Glory, but ſuch as, through the Kingdome of Grace, ſubmit themſelves, in the Kingdome of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell,</hi> to <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> his his Lawes, and Authority.</p>
                     <pb n="179" facs="tcp:152049:102"/>
                     <p>Now, in this inferiour part of his Kingdome, which is the Kingdome of Grace, there is not the beſt ſubject, but is ſubject to tanſgreſſe, though through infirmity, yet not through wilfull Rebellion. But in the ſuperior part, which is the Kingdome of Glory, there ſhall not be the leaſt omiſſion of good, nor the leaſt commiſſion of evill; but all our thoughts, words, and workes, ſhall wholly tend to the glory of our Celeſtiall King, and Governour. For when ſin, and the old Serpent, ſhall be caſt into the bottome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit, we ſhall have no
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:152049:103" rendition="simple:additions"/> temptations, but ſhall ſing, <hi>Bleſsing, glory, honour, and power be unto him, that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth upon the Throne, and the Lambe for ever-more. Rev.</hi> 5.13.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.13</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>What remaines now, but that with the Queene of <hi>Sheba,</hi> we ſet forward out of our owne Countrey, the World, to ſee, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the Wiſedome, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Peace, Power, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Magnificence of our Heavenly <hi>Solomon,</hi> here entitled, <hi>King of the Iewes.</hi> She was a Queene, we ſubjects; ſhee came from farre, we have our <hi>Solomon</hi> amongſt us; ſhee ſought a meere Man, we
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:152049:103" rendition="simple:additions"/> may finde one who is both God, and Man, ſhee gave preſents, we ſhall receive rewards: Let not the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> then riſe up in Judgement againſt us, for behold, a greater than <hi>Solomon</hi> is here. Seeke him then (O ſanctified Soule) ſeeke him with devotion, for he is <hi>Ieſus, A Saviour:</hi> ſeeke him by imitation, for he is <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renus, A ſweet ſmelling Flower:</hi> ſeeke him by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and obedience, for he is <hi>Rex Iudaeorum, King of the Iewes:</hi> ſeeke him for thy refection, ſeeke him for thy protection, for he is the Seed of the Woman,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:152049:104"/> that breakes the Serpents Head: It is hee that is the keeper of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Salvation of his people: It is he that will ſlay all thine, and his enemies, that would not have him reigne over them. Though that great Dragon, old Serpent, and roaring Lyon ſeeke to devoure thee, yet ſeeke thy King, and Saviour, and hee will defend thee: Of thy ſelfe, thou art <hi>Debilis ad operandum, facilis ad ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducendum, fragilis ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtendum: Vnable to doe well, eaſie to be ſeduced, and weake to reſiſt:</hi> Yet the Name of <hi>Ieſus of Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, King of the Iewes,</hi> is a
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:152049:104"/> ſtrong Tower, to fly unto; for under that thou ſhalt be ſecure. Feare not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for hee is thy ſhield, and exceeding great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: <hi>Hee is that God of peace, that ſhall ſhortly tread downe Satan under thy feete. Rom.</hi> 16.20.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20.</note> Feare not the <hi>Law,</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſatisfied it; where <hi>Moſes</hi> launceth, <hi>Ieſus</hi> cureth; where the <hi>Law</hi> ſearcheth, the <hi>Goſpell</hi> ſalveth. Feare not thy ſinnes, if thou doeſt weepe for them; for this <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> calleth <hi>all that are wearie, and heavie la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and hee will refreſh them.</hi> Feare not the world,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:152049:105"/> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath overcome the world: It is he <hi>Qui pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat pro te,</hi> it is he, <hi>qui pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat in te: It is he that fights for thee againſt the world, it is he that fights in thee by his grace.</hi> Feare not the ungodly, for thy King is a righteous, and ſevere King, who ſhall one day ſit in Judgement, giving <hi>Praemium, &amp; Paenam, Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and Reward;</hi> the recompenſe of Reward to a faithfull ſubject, and the paine of Damnation to trayterous rebells: For he is a juſt Judge, whom ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bribes can allure, nor gifts entice, nor threats can alter from doing right.</p>
                     <pb n="185" facs="tcp:152049:105"/>
                     <p>Oh then ſeeke this <hi>Ieſus,</hi> ſeeke this <hi>Nazarenus,</hi> ſeeke this <hi>King of Iewes:</hi> Seeke him for thy Lord, and hee will finde thee for his inheritance; inſtall him for thy King, and he will enfranchiſe thee for his ſubject; admit him for thy Governour, and hee will admit thee to glory, and immortality. For his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is not of this world below, but of the world above, as was typified by placing this Title above his Head, not under his Feete.</p>
                     <p>Oh then, deare Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, come out of the world, and out of this dangerous,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:152049:106"/> and dreadfull ſecurity of the Fleſh: Whatſoever ſeemes glorious to the eye, odoriferous to the ſmell, harmonious to the eare, delicate to the taſte, and ſoft to the touch, O forſake them all, to follow <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Awake oh thou <hi>Soule</hi> that ſleepeſt, for the Lord is come: Hee is come with <hi>Salvation,</hi> he is come with <hi>Vertue,</hi> hee is come with <hi>Glory:</hi> For <hi>Ieſus</hi> commeth not without <hi>Salvation,</hi> nor <hi>Nazarenus</hi> without <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue;</hi> nor <hi>The King of the Iewes</hi> without <hi>Glory.</hi> Bee of good comfort thou loſt ſheepe, <hi>Ieſus</hi> is come to
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:152049:106"/> ſeeke, and to ſave that which was loſt: Bee of good comfort, thou la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting ſinner, <hi>Nazare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> is come to decke thee with ornaments of Grace: Be of good comfort, thou that aſpireſt to true Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, for <hi>The King of the Iewes,</hi> will make thee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of his Kingdome.</p>
                     <p>If thou ſeeke this <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> thou muſt ſeeke him with Humility; for hee was Humility it ſelfe: Hee, inſteed of a Crowne of Gold, was content for thy ſake, with a Crowne of Thornes; for Regall attire, with a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple garment, yea, goary
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:152049:107"/> wounds; for a Kingly Scepter, a Reede in his hand; for a Throne, the Croſſe; for joyfull Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, blaſphemous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations; for delicate dainties, Vineger, and Gall: Oh ſeeke him then in Humility, for pride a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendeth not with the King of Humility, nor ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, with the God of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; nor Luſt with a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin-ſonne of a Virgin-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; nor wickedneſſe with the Juſt one. And if thou bee a ſubject of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, bee not like the Swine, <hi>Qui Roſas projici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, ut lutum quaerant: Who reject the ſweet Roſe, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:152049:107"/> the ſtinking mire.</hi> Oh never conforme thy ſelfe to this world, bee not of that durty generation: but ſince thy <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> is in Heaven, let thy converſation be in Heaven alſo: let the World, and her brave vanities goe which way they will; bee thou (as <hi>Anſelme</hi> ſayes ſweetly) <hi>Corpore ambulans in Terra, ſed corde habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans in Coelo: One that walkes on Earth with thy Body, but dwelleſt in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with thy Heart.</hi> Get out from thine owne Countrey, the World; from thine owne Kinred, the Fleſh; and from thy
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:152049:108"/> Fathers Houſe, the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Satan, unto the Land, which the Lord hath ſhewen thee, even that Kingdome, which the <hi>King of the Iewes</hi> hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for thee: where thou ſhalt behold <hi>Pulchrum Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum, pulchrum Regnum, Regem pulcherrimum: A glorious Aſſembly of Saints, a glorious Kingdome, but a King moſt glorious:</hi> where wee ſhall ſhine in Glory, and Brightneſſe, with Albes of Innocency on our backes, Palmes of Victory in our Hands, Crownes of Glory on our Heads, and Songs of Tryumph in our Mouthes:
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:152049:108"/> then ſhall wee enter into <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum, Into the Holy of Holies;</hi> there ſhall wee celebrate <hi>Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Sabbatorum, The Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath of Sabbaths:</hi> Then ſhall wee ſing <hi>Canticum Canticorum, The Song of Songs,</hi> which none can learne, but thoſe that are redeemed from the Earth: Then ſhall we give eternall Honour, Glory, and Praiſe to him that was, is, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall bee, <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth, King of the Iewes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:152049:14"/>
               <head>The Authors Prayer to <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth, King of the Jewes,</hi> collected out of the fore-going Diſcourſe.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Jeſus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Thou Sonne of God, and ſweete Saviour of the World; <hi>Bone Ieſu, eſto mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi Ieſus:</hi> Thou art made unto us of God, <hi>Wiſedome, Righteouſneſſe, Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152049:15"/> and <hi>Redemption: Wiſedome,</hi> by thy Word preached; <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> by our ſinnes pardoned, <hi>Sanctification,</hi> by thy grace infuſed; and <hi>Redemption,</hi> by thy paines ſuſtained: Have mercy upon us miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſinners: Oh, our bleſſed Saviour, who haſt borne our ſorrows, ſhed our teares, ſuffered our diſgrace, ſuſtained our pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and payd our debt, inſpire us with thy Holy Spirit, that, though the <hi>Iewes, Turkes,</hi> and Infidels revile thee, wee may ſtill honour thee; though they blaſpheme
<pb facs="tcp:152049:15"/> thy Name <hi>Ieſus,</hi> we may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore it; though they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute it, we may make it our refuge: For thy Name (ô <hi>Ieſus</hi>) is a ſtrong Tower, the righteous flye unto it, and are ſecured. Though <hi>Iewes, Turkes,</hi> and <hi>Heathen</hi> diſdaine thy Name, yet give us Grace, that we may eſtimate it, to be a precious Oyntment powred out; though they vilifie it, let us (ſweet <hi>Ieſu</hi>) ſtill glory in it; for with the Lord there is Juſtice, but with thee, Oh Saviour, there is plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <hi>Redemption:</hi> Oh Lord, what <hi>Pilate</hi> deem'd to be thy ſhame, prooves
<pb facs="tcp:152049:16"/> to be thy glory; he writes thee diſgracefully <hi>Ieſus</hi> with his hand, whom he could not call faithfully <hi>Ieſus</hi> with his heart: Yet will we ever acknowledge <hi>Ieſus,</hi> to be thy Name, and <hi>Ieſus</hi> is thy Nature; <hi>Ieſus</hi> by Title, a <hi>Saviour</hi> by Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. With this Name <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> thy Birth was honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and with this Name <hi>Ieſus,</hi> thy Death was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured: What thou brought'ſt into the world, by the Angels Direction, thou carriedſt out of the world, by <hi>Pilates</hi> Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: To thee therefore, (I ſay once more) and will
<pb facs="tcp:152049:16"/> never ceaſe ſaying, and praying, <hi>Bone Ieſu, eſto mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi Ieſus;</hi> O good <hi>Ieſu,</hi> be thou to me a Saviour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Nazarenus, ſanctified.</head>
                  <p>OH Holy <hi>Nazarenus,</hi> who waſt ſanctified in the wombe, and out of the wombe; whoſe Humane Nature was full of Grace, and Truth; full of Grace, in thy Workes; full of Truth, in thy Words; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in thy Birth; holy, in thy Life; and holy, in thy Death; vouchſafe to looke upon us miſerable ſinners,
<pb facs="tcp:152049:17"/> who were conceived in ſinne, and borne in iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Sanctifie us with thy holy Spirit, that from thee, wee may derive ſuch holineſſe of life, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, that all our thoughts, words, and workes, being through thy Grace, ſanctified, may be pleaſing, and acceptable unto thee, who haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to be holy, as thou art holy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Nazarenus, ſeparated.</head>
                  <p>O Loving <hi>Nazarenus,</hi> thou, who wert that
<pb facs="tcp:152049:17"/> Scape-goate, ſeparated from thy fellows, to make an attonement for the ſins of the world; thou, that waſt ſeparated from thy Fathers Court of Majeſty, by taking upon thee the forme of a Servant; thou that waſt ſeparated from thine owne Nation, when thou fleddeſt into <hi>Egypt,</hi> for feare of <hi>Herod;</hi> thou, that waſt ſeparated from thy Brethren, and Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke, to doe thy Fathers Will; thou, that waſt ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from thy Diſciples, when thou hungſt upon the Croſſe; thou, that waſt ſeparated from the living,
<pb facs="tcp:152049:18"/> when thou dyedſt for our Redemption; thou, that waſt ſeparated from the World, when thou aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedſt into Heaven; vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to looke with the eyes of pitty, and compaſſion upon us, moſt wretched, and miſerable Caitiffes; ſeparate our ſinnes farre from us, as farre as is the Eaſt from the Weſt, blot them all out of thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, caſt them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde thy backe, drowne them in the bottome of the Sea, that they may never riſe up againſt us, to make a wall of ſeparation, between thee and our poore ſoules.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152049:18"/>
                  <head>Nazarenus, Flos, <hi>or</hi> Floridus.</head>
                  <p>OH thou flouriſhing <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarenus,</hi> thou ſweete ſmelling Flower, ſprung out of the ſtemme of <hi>Ieſſe:</hi> Thou fragrant Roſe of <hi>Sharon,</hi> thou white Lilly of the Valleyes; thou, who containeſt all ſweetneſſe in thy ſelfe, in regard of the ſweetneſſe of thy Vertues, manifeſted in thy holy converſation; wherein thou art a ſweet ſmelling Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for imitation: Thou, that doeſt impart thy
<pb facs="tcp:152049:19"/> ſweetneſſe to us, in regard of thy Paſſion; wherein thou didſt offer thy ſelfe to God, a Sacrifice of a ſweete ſmelling ſavour, for our Reconciliation.</p>
                  <p>Oh thou eternall ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which wee ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy hereafter, in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, draw us, with thy delicious O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, after thee, yea, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: Lead us into thy Garden, and comfort us with the fragrancy of thy Celeſtiall Flowers, the <hi>Violet,</hi> the <hi>Lilly,</hi> the <hi>Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron,</hi> the <hi>Roſe,</hi> and the <hi>Marygold;</hi> nay, make us (O bleſſed <hi>Nazarenus</hi>)
<pb facs="tcp:152049:19"/> ſpirituall Gardens to thy ſelfe; ſet in our Hearts, ſome ſlippes of thoſe Flowers, purge us from the weeds of Vice, and Wickedneſſe; as Pride, Deceit, Gluttony, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, Envy, Malice, and Diſobedience; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed thereof, make Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to flouriſh in our cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, Innocency, in our converſations, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in our appetites, Charity, in our affections, and Obedience, in all our actions, to the ſalvation of our ſoules, the good example of others, and to the glory, and praiſe of
<pb facs="tcp:152049:20"/> thee, our ſweete <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>King of the Iewes.</head>
                  <p>OH Thou Soveraigne Monarch of Heaven, and Earth, reigning in Heaven, by thy Glory, in Earth, by thy Grace; and in Hell, by thy Juſtice: Oh thou <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> who haſt ſole power to command our Soules, take us into thy protection, who flie under the ſhadow of thy wings: Oh ſuffer us not to deny our Alleageance unto thee; let us never
<pb facs="tcp:152049:20"/> make any confederacy, or enthrall our ſelves to the World, the Fleſh, or the Divell, who are Enemies unto thee, and would faine bring us into ſubjection unto them, get the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over us, and make us their vaſſals. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all worldlings, gluttons, drunkards, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane perſons, and all that doe continue in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, have made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bond-ſlaves unto theſe Tyrants; yet grant, ô powerfull King, that we, whom thou haſt called to the inheritance of thy
<pb facs="tcp:152049:21"/> Saints, in love, ſtand faſt in the liberty, wherwith thou haſt made us free, not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering our ſoules to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled againe, with the yoake of bondage: Wee know, that their ſervice is nothing but miſery, and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny; the World will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us, the Fleſh will infect us, and the Devill will deſtroy us; from ſuch Kings, good Lord deliver us. Onely thou, ô bleſſed <hi>King of the Iewes,</hi> be our ſpirituall Soveraigne; thou art wiſe, and wilt inſtruct us; thou art liberall, and wilt reward us; thou art mighty, and wilt defend
<pb facs="tcp:152049:21"/> us; thou art juſt, and wilt not forget us; thou art ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, and wilt not ſuffer the wicked to tryumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us; thou art peaceable, and wilt give us peace with God, peace with our Neighbours, and peace with our owne Soules, which is the peace of a good Conſcience: Yea, thou art our peace, who haſt wrought our Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation with God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; to whom, with thee oh <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth, King of the Iewes,</hi> and the Holy Ghoſt, our everlaſting Comforter, be all honour, and glory, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:152049:22"/>
               <head>A Prayer to <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth, King of the Iewes,</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the Church, and all the Members thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Thou ſweete Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the World, thou Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iuda;</hi> thou fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant Roſe, ſprung from the Roote of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> wee
<pb facs="tcp:152049:22"/> humbly beſeech thee, to bleſſe thy Univerſall Church diſperſed, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed over the face of the Earth: and therein com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort all thoſe that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe, ſtrengthen thoſe that are weake, uphold them that ſtand, raiſe up them that are fallen: Send helpe, comfort, and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in thy good time, to all thy Children, that bee in ſorrow, neede, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, miſery, or any other adverſity.</p>
               <p>More eſpecially, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, to bleſſe this Church, and Common-weale wherein wee live,
<pb facs="tcp:152049:23"/> enter not into Judgement with the crying ſinnes of the Land, but firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from us our ſinnes, and then, in mercy, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy heavy Judgments, which are already fallen upon us; and, which is greatly to be feared, will every day, more, and more, befall us, unleſſe with true, and unfeigned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance wee turne unto thee, <hi>O Ieſu,</hi> who art both willing, and able to ſave all thoſe, that flye to thee for ſuccour.</p>
               <p>Continue, wee humbly beſeech thee, the rich trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of thy Goſpell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb facs="tcp:152049:23"/> us, give it a free paſſage dayly, more, and more; convert, or elſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found all thoſe, that are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies unto the ſame, and which ſeeke to overthrow that Church, which thine owne Right hand hath planted, and whereof thou thy ſelfe art the chiefe corner-ſtone, ſometimes of the Builders refuſed: Reforme thoſe things which are amiſſe in thy Church, and grant, that thy Glorious Majeſty, may bee exalted in this Nation ever-more, in ſincere, pure, and holy worſhipping of thee.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152049:24"/>
               <p>To this end, O good God, powre downe all thy bleſſings, both ſpirituall, and temporall, upon thy deare Servant, and our moſt gracious Soveraigne, whom thou haſt appointed to rule over us, CHARLES, by thy gracious goodneſſe, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Faith, &amp;c. Bleſſe him with thy ſaving Health, annoint thine An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted, with the ſweete ſenting Oyle of Joy, and Gladneſſe, above all his fellows: Let the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy Honour, and Glory, be the chiefeſt aime
<pb facs="tcp:152049:24"/> of his deſires; give unto him a more than ordinarie ſtrength, courage, and magnanimity, fit to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine, and beare the weight of ſo heavy a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, as the weight of ſo many Kingdomes are: Grant unto him the Spirit of Wiſedome, diſcretion, and government, that with all Equity, and Juſtice, hee may theſe his Kingdomes peaceably, and quietly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne: Defend him from all forraigne invaſions, and from the miſchievous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of domeſticall Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; ſcatter all his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies abroad, make them
<pb facs="tcp:152049:25"/> like water ſpilt upon the earth, never to be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up againe: bleſſe him in life, with many happy dayes; in death, with the peace of <hi>Syon;</hi> and in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, with the ioyes of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe.</p>
               <p>Blesse together with him, with abundance of bleſſings, ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>all, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Majeſties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Queene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Charles,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> excellent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Siſter, with</p>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
